<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rule of charity: or, The liberal mans guide design'd, for the use of all good Christians. Being the pious result of a lay-man's ordinary meditations. By H.W. Gent. Licensed according to order.</title>
            <author>H. W. (Henry Waring)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219405</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830881</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830881</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35343</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67603)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35343)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1879:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rule of charity: or, The liberal mans guide design'd, for the use of all good Christians. Being the pious result of a lay-man's ordinary meditations. By H.W. Gent. Licensed according to order.</title>
                  <author>H. W. (Henry Waring)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 100 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year, MDCXC. [1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Henry Waring.</note>
                  <note>Copy has print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35343:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RULE OF CHARITY: OR, THE Liberal Mans Guide; Deſign'd, For the Uſe of all good CHRISTIANS.</p>
            <p>Being the Pious Reſult of a <hi>Lay-Man</hi>'s Ordinary Meditations.</p>
            <p>By <hi>H.W.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, in the Year, MDCXC.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35343:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35343:3"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable, Sir <hi>Thomas Rokeby,</hi> Kt. One of Their Majeſties Judges of the Court of Common-Bench.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>REligion</hi> being not that <hi>Melancholy</hi> Piece, that Obligeth us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Unſociable,</hi> and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to all that hath any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to <hi>Chearfulneſs &amp; Plenty;</hi> but rather <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:35343:4"/>us, how to make uſe of <hi>Both,</hi> ſo as we may beſt enjoy our Selves, and benefit Others: I hope that inherent Goodneſs, which hath rendered you ſo Remarkable for your <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> will not refuſe <hi>Her</hi> now Your <hi>Refuge,</hi> when by Your Noble Diſpoſitions ſhe is En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd, not only to pretend to, but confidently Plead a juſt Title to your <hi>Patronage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, the <hi>Receders</hi> from this <hi>Duty,</hi> neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards her <hi>Rule,</hi> nor owns her <hi>Practice,</hi> but are afraid of all that carries the Face of <hi>Love,</hi> and true <hi>Munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence;</hi> and are only Valiant in breaking thoſe holy <hi>Laws,</hi> which <hi>Heaven</hi> hath made <hi>Eternal:</hi> That would have no ſuch <hi>Images</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the World, as the <hi>Diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;</hi> and ſeem to believe, <hi>Liberality,</hi> at beſt, but a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Superſtition.</p>
            <p>But let theſe, I ſay, do Right to <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and Confeſs, it was no Aſperſion thrown upon our <hi>Religion,</hi> when he gave out,
<pb facs="tcp:35343:5"/>there was nothing in it beyond a <hi>Mode</hi> of Believing, that will not allow her Sacred <hi>Sanction,</hi> nor ſubmit to the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Charity;</hi> but had rather acknowledge Her a <hi>Popiſh,</hi> or an <hi>Italian Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> than have Her <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliz'd</hi> here, to the Prejudice of the <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This part of it, that is here preſented, is but the Imperfect Effigie of the <hi>Precept,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by one that is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, render'd by his ill <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,</hi> too great a Dependent on its Mandates.</p>
            <p>I know You would even dote upon the <hi>Piece,</hi> were it well <hi>Drawn,</hi> becauſe it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for <hi>Right-Reaſon,</hi> to reſiſt the Charms of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> Painted in good Colours to the full Proportion.</p>
            <p>My Ambition, at preſent, extends but to Your <hi>Pardon,</hi> not to Your <hi>Eſteem;</hi> and it is my Requeſt, that where it cannot be admitted as a <hi>Counſel,</hi> it may ſerve for an <hi>Admonition:</hi> Hoping you will have the ſame Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb facs="tcp:35343:6"/>for the <hi>Vertue,</hi> and not look upon Her as the leſs a <hi>Beauty,</hi> becauſe I have ſhew'd Her in ſo mean a <hi>Habit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charity</hi> takes moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in her Self, when ſhe goes <hi>Plaineſt,</hi> and is in a Dreſs of <hi>Condeſcention;</hi> affecting no Garbe ſo <hi>Little,</hi> as that of a <hi>Great Fortune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you diſcern Imperfections in the <hi>Copy,</hi> let not <hi>Charity</hi> for my Sake, fall under an <hi>Imputation;</hi> That needs no ſuch <hi>Advocate</hi> as I am, nor ſuch a Common <hi>Pen,</hi> but one from an <hi>Angels</hi> Wing, to advance Her <hi>Eſteem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a Beauty in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> exceeding that of <hi>State;</hi> and a Glory in <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> Superior to the proud Inſcript of <hi>Monarchs:</hi> Both of theſe waits upon <hi>Charity,</hi> and are the proper Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Her <hi>Profeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here the known Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy which ſome Perſons viſibly Bares to the diſregarders of this <hi>Duty,</hi> diverts my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Pen, believing it not
<pb facs="tcp:35343:7"/>Pertinent to be too <hi>Nice</hi> in my Deſcription of that, which hath been already ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently well expreſſed in your <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Converſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſideration of which, obliges me to an unwilling Silence, by Humbly taking leave to Subſcribe my Self,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Moſt Faithful, and Moſt Devoted Servant To Command, Henry Waring.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35343:7"/>
            <head>THE Rule of Charity.</head>
            <p>IF an Authors Place or Degree that he holdeth, can add Vertue to Words, or ſerve to procure Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Crown of <hi>Solomon</hi> will oblige you to hear a King newly become a Preacher: (The Richeſt Monarch that ever Reign'd in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Wiſeſt of Eaſtern Sophies, ſteps from the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> to the Chair of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and Teacheth us,) <hi>Eccleſ.</hi>11.4. <hi>Caſt thy Bread upon the Water, and after many days thou ſhalt find it.</hi> This is not an ordinary Rule of Human Policy, but the Doctrine of true Religion, by which Men are beſt Govern'd. Commentators agree, That theſe words of the Preacher, <hi>[Caſt thy Bread upon the Water,]</hi> exhort us to the Relief of all ſuch as are Diſtreſt; which the Verſe following doth Illuſtrate: But
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35343:8"/>when they came to Expound the ſingle words of that Text, they differ: A few ſay <hi>[Caſt thy Bread]</hi> that is, The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or matter whereof Bread is made <hi>[upon the Water,]</hi> that is, A fruitful Soyl, <hi>[and thou ſhalt find it,]</hi> that is, Reap it again, <hi>[after many days,]</hi> that is, In time of Harveſt; theſe make the Precept of <hi>Charity</hi> to become an <hi>Allegory.</hi> Let us rather ſay, <hi>Theſe Alms we beſtow, are as Seed diſperſed, and the Poor receives a Soyl ſo Fertile, that daily beſtowing our</hi> Charity, <hi>we Sow with a large hand, not without aſſurance of receiving an ample re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of Eternal Rewards.</hi> This Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the plaineſt, only this acceptation of the word <hi>[Bread]</hi> ſeems harſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual; yet we ſhall find that <hi>Bread</hi> may be taken for <hi>Alms,</hi> while we converſe with the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> (the Original <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>Lehem,</hi> which we commonly Tranſlate <hi>Bread,</hi> is taken in the Scripture for all ſorts of Proviſion; in that ſenſe you may read it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Lehem</hi> ſignifies the fleſh of Beaſts Sacrificed, <hi>Levit.</hi> 3.11. It is uſed for the Fruit of Trees, <hi>Jer.</hi>11.19.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35343:8"/>
               <hi>Lehem</hi> is alſo taken for the Fodder of Cattle, <hi>Pſal.</hi>14.7, 9. becauſe the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Language conſiſteth of few words, ſo that every word beareth many ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; which is the reaſon that <hi>Lehem</hi> (among the <hi>Jews</hi>) did ſometimes import all manner of ſubſiſtence, every thing that Man or Beaſt uſed to live upon; in which ſenſe it is taken in the <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> when we Pray for <hi>Daily Bread,</hi> and in a larger Extent there, implying not only the neceſſaries of our Body, but alſo that Angels food, (that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> , <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3.) the <hi>Bleſſed Sacrament,</hi> by which our Souls are nouriſht for <hi>Eternity:</hi> But moſt Divines underſtands the word <hi>Bread,</hi> in the <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical</hi> ſenſe, placing the Figure in the word <hi>Waters,</hi> which carries divers In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations: Some Authors will have theſe words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> recommended to us, <hi>Giving of Alms at all adventure, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having an Eye to the recompence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward:</hi> As if we were adviſed to caſt our <hi>Bread</hi> upon thoſe rouling and inconſtant <hi>Waves,</hi> that will ſooner float away with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35343:9"/>our <hi>Eſtates,</hi> than return us (in this or the next life) a laudable <hi>Cargo:</hi> But the Beſt and Wiſeſt, deliver the words in a contrary Senſe, which is indeed moſt <hi>Catholick,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal;</hi> affirming, To caſt our <hi>Bread</hi> (or <hi>Charity</hi>) upon <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s Waters, is the ſafeſt and ſpeedieſt way to Merchandize and Trade with Heaven; where, in exchange for ſome ſmall tokens of Chriſtian Love, and cheap inſtances of Compaſſion, we ſhall receive ſecret aſſurances in this Life of future Mercy, attended with publick Bleſſings; and, in the next, an Eternal weight of Glory. Either ſuch another Fiſh as came to diſcharge the Tax for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſhall repay our Bounty into our Boſom, or ſome <hi>Dolphin</hi> ſhall make good our Adventure: That <hi>Bread</hi> you ſo graciouſly beſtow, ſhall not fail to be returned with Advantage, as the Ring of St. <hi>Arnold,</hi> in the Legend; or that of <hi>Polycratus,</hi> in <hi>Herodotus.</hi> The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church further ingage us to beſtow our <hi>Bread,</hi> or works of <hi>Mercy,</hi> with <hi>Waters;</hi> that is, our <hi>Alms</hi> moiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35343:9"/>with tears of <hi>Pity;</hi> as if a liberal hand in the <hi>Donor,</hi> ſhould be prompted to give, by the ſecret Motions of the Bowels of Compaſſion; and that the Sluces of <hi>Grief</hi> ſhould remain open, to render the <hi>Charity</hi> Perfect.</p>
            <p>Some would have the <hi>Waters</hi> here, ſignifie diſtreſſed Merchants, poor Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Paſſengers, that in their way of living, are compelled to ſtruggle with an Ocean of Danger; ſo much indeed the word carries, and more; for by <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> all infirm and decayed perſons, all people of the meaneſt condition are ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, [<hi>Apocalyps</hi> 17.15.] ſuch as creep into their Graves in Silence, that come and go without notice, that paſs away from this World without any noiſe of Revenge, or pomp of Ceremonious La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation. The vulgar, the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of Men, are denoted by the word <hi>Waters,</hi> becauſe they are very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous in their Uſe and Exceſſes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettled in their Condition, always Rouling this way and t'other; their Temper is Weak, their Motions Irregular, always
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35343:10"/>in Perturbation; every Hurricane of State, Wind of falſe Doctrine, Tempeſt of Fears and Jealouſies, tranſports and hurries them hither and thither, ſo as they can remain at no certainty. The Poet made ſuch a Remark upon them, and hath ſuited the Epithet of <hi>Moveable,</hi> to their Inconſtancy; <hi>(Mobile vulgus,)</hi> whoſe humour and departure the <hi>Royal Prophet</hi> ſo well underſtood, that he thought he could compare the raging of the Sea, to nothing more properly, than to the Madneſs of the People. So when he telleth us, <hi>The Waves of the Sea are gone over his head, and entered into his Soul,</hi> Pſal. 69. he meaneth, the Inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Rabble; for it exceedingly troubled <hi>David,</hi> to ſee the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo prone to <hi>Rebellion.</hi> The firſt <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Bibles of <hi>Tyndal</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus</hi> have it, <hi>[Lay thy Bread upon wet Faces,]</hi> that is, upon all people in a Mourning condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that water their Couches with their Tears, and appear lamentable Objects of your Pity and Compaſſion. St. <hi>Jerom</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone Interprets the words in this manner,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35343:10"/>[<hi>Caſt thy Bread,</hi>] that is, place the Word of God [<hi>upon the Waters,</hi>] that is, <hi>Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Souls;</hi> intimating, that you are not to give your wholeſome Doctrine of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to ſuch as will have you in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion. Such another Caution as that, is offered us, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 32. 4. <hi>Not to be Wiſe unſeaſonably,</hi>(<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) for ſo ſhall we looſe the good Seed of Chriſtian Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions and Reproofs, upon Hearts ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate and impenitent. 'Tis a breach of that Precept, <hi>Mat.7. To caſt Pearls before Swine,</hi> by offering a <hi>Creed</hi> to thoſe that are ready to throw Contempt upon the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> word [<hi>Caſt</hi>] in the two famous Tranſlations of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches, is the ſame with <hi>Sow, Send,</hi> or <hi>Scatter:</hi> The Truth is, the firſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlators were no very good Linguiſts, but made an eaſie miſtake of the letter <hi>Caph</hi> for <hi>Cheth,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) WHEREAS THE ORIGINAL WORD IS <hi>Shallah,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) they Conſtrued it as <hi>Shallach,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) making a notorious difference in ſignification; for the latter imports De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation and Judgment, the former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35343:11"/>in giving; the one ſounds as if we never could beſtow too much; the other, that a Man as ſoon giveth too much as too little: Theſe Interpretations do well together, and ſo long as they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us divers excellent Rules of Practice, we may admit both as Orthodox. All objects of <hi>Charity</hi> are here deſigned by the word <hi>Waters;</hi> that is, the ſeveral parts of Mankind, all ſuch as appear Poor, Infirm, or any way Miſerable; Captives and Gally-ſlaves, Exiles, decayed Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants or Tradeſmen, diſtreſſed Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Schollars not prefer'd, impoveriſh'd Houſe-keepers, that through too much Truſt, and too many bad Debts, are forc'd into Sanctuary; Widows and Orphans, that are left Friendleſs and Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; Sick or Maimed Laborours, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Travellers, and weeping Penitent Strangers, and all that are deſtitute of Friends and Comfort, that with dejected Countenances implore your Pity. The World affords us ſuch variety of ſad Objects, that the Writer might turn his Catalogue into a Volum: Some want
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35343:11"/>Advice, ſome Law, ſome Religion, ſome Friends, ſome Medicines; yes, and ſo numerous are Human wants and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that I want room and leiſure to expreſs the number of ſuch as are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by Heaven to receive your Charity; yet all come here under the name and notion of <hi>Waters:</hi> Is it not pity, to ſee the lean and naked Cripple, that hath a Stomach, to deſire Bread, but wanteth Hands to receive it; or that Blind <hi>Lazar,</hi> deprived of Eyes, wherewith he might behold his own Nakedneſs; or the Man that is rob'd of his Taſte and Feeling, by Icy diſtempers, or grievous Caſualties? Have you never beheld the treacherous Limbs of ſome people, Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away before their Faces? Some have their Spirits ſo darkned, they guide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, while Reaſon hath loſt the right uſe of her Organs; others ſadly want common Senſe, to diſtinguiſh the Food that is ſafe, from that which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſome; ſhewing us where Nature will leave us, when we are forſaken by Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35343:12"/>
            <p>There remains yet another Querae, raiſed from theſe words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> (<hi>Caſt thy Bread upon the Waters,</hi>) Whether the Royal Preacher did intend them for a Precept, or a Councel? The One doth abſolutely oblige, the Other recommends a matter of Practice; If a Precept, the words muſt be included in the Moral Law, and univerſally Bind all perſons of Ability. Were it no more than found Advice, ſome Men only ſhould obſerve it, in ſome Caſes; but take it (as it is) for a part of that Eternal Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (which ought to influence all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, I might have ſaid, all Creatures,) What living thing is there in the World, that doth not communicate ſome bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to its fellows? and by conſequence, ſheweth it ſelf loving and ſerviceable to the other parts of the Creation. And ſhall Man alone degenerate? Shall be that is Maſter of Reaſon, ſhew himſelf a Beaſt to his Companions, whilſt the moſt Irrational part of the Univerſe teacheth him the way to be Charitable? Let him not know, how to prove unkind to his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35343:12"/>Fellows; that cannot but know, how much he hath received from our good Maſter.</p>
            <p>You may prove <hi>Solomon</hi>'s words a part of the Law of Nature, by thoſe indelible Characters of the <hi>Soul,</hi> that exert their Powers in the practiſe of Pagans. We find among thoſe people, that are yet in the ſhadow, poſitive Rules of <hi>doing Good,</hi> both to their own, and to Strangers; which not deriving themſelves from the Edicts of Divine Revelation, muſt be aſcribed to the provident Dictates of Nature.</p>
            <p>But we may better prove <hi>Alms</hi> a Duty, from the expreſs Reaſon of Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; wherein <hi>Uncharitableneſs</hi> is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as a grievous Sin, becauſe it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Love of <hi>God,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contradicts the meaning of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Precepts.</p>
            <p>That moſt eminent <hi>Seer</hi> puts the Queſtion, 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 3.17. <hi>He that ſeeth his Brother in want, and ſhutteth up his Bowels of Compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?</hi> The Querae there
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35343:13"/>(as in ſeveral other places in the <hi>Bible,</hi>) is put for a vehement <hi>Negative;</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, that in obdurate hearts, the Love of <hi>God</hi> cannot be Reſident. The Prayers of <hi>Uncharitable</hi> people are not anſwered; for <hi>God</hi> giveth us, becauſe he percieves us free to give, and forgive others: <hi>He that ſtoppeth his ears at the cries of the Poor, ſhall cry himſelf, and not be heard,</hi> was a Proverb in <hi>Jury,</hi> and continues a great Truth all the World over, (<hi>Prov.</hi> 21. 13.) for ſo <hi>God</hi> delights to retalliate with his Creatures.</p>
            <p>Want of Love (in us) occaſions our Wants, and beſpeaks Unhappineſs for us in this Life, and in the next, everlaſting Perdition. There is not another Sin charg'd upon Damn'd <hi>Dives,</hi> beſides his want of <hi>Charity;</hi> and thoſe Wretches that are mentioned in St. <hi>Math.</hi> 25. were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned only for their unkindneſs to the Brethren, and their groſs defects in the viſible part of this Duty.</p>
            <p>You would ask, In what part of the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> the Rule of <hi>Charity</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd? <hi>Bellarmine</hi> following <hi>Aquinas,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35343:13"/>refers it to the <hi>Fifth Commandment,</hi> which includes all Rights appertaining to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, Equals, and Inferiors; and of this laſt ſort, the Poor are Principals: And of all Duties belonging to the Poor, <hi>Alms</hi> is moſt conſiderable; and there is ſcarce any thing that we are oblig'd to do for them, but comes within the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other Authors derive this Duty from the <hi>Eighth Commandment,</hi> and will have <hi>Robbery</hi> to be but one and the ſame thing with <hi>Uncharitableneſs;</hi> affirming, That he that is able to Give, and withholds his <hi>Alms</hi> from thoſe that Want, and call for his Relief, Robs his poor Neighbour of his juſt Comfort, and <hi>God</hi> of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Therefore, the Phraiſe is changed, St. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 9. and <hi>Solomons</hi> Precept, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Evangelical Law; where it is not left at our choice, to do good; but we are charged to make us <hi>Friends with the Mammon of Unrighteouſneſs.</hi> 'Tis cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Unrighteous Mammon,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> not only when it is unjuſtly acquir'd, but alſo while it is Uncharitably detain'd
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35343:14"/>from thoſe that are Neceſſitated. Is it commendable, that I live in ſuperfluous manner, while my poor Brother wanteth to ſuffice Nature? Sure, it is a wrong to withhold from the Poor what I can eaſily ſpare, in their Affliction and Extremity. <hi>Superflua diviti neceſſaria ſunt Pauperi, aliena retinet qui iſta tenet. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Rich mans Exceedings, are the Poor mans Portion;</hi> ſo as he unjuſtly ſeems to Defraud others, that reſerves to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more than is ſufficient.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in a rougher Dialect, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <hi>It is no leſs Criminal, for Rich per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to deny Neceſſitated people Relief, than to take from them that they have, and uſe violence to the Laws of Property.</hi> Yes, and ſome proceed further, reducing theſe words of <hi>Solomon</hi> to the <hi>Sixth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> making <hi>Uncharitable</hi> Men no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Murderers;</hi> agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that of <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 34. 21. <hi>The Bread of the Needy, is their Life; he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraudeth them thereof, is a Man of Blood.</hi> So that we ſee, to detain neceſſary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion from them that Want, is to ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35343:14"/>the lives of Poor men; and, as much as in us lies, to deprive him of Succeſſion, it is to Famiſh our afflicted Neighbour, (the ſharpeſt of all Deaths) and in him to ſeek to Murther his Poſterity.</p>
            <p>You hear how this Edict of <hi>Alms,</hi> has been referred to <hi>Three</hi> of the <hi>Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> yet more properly belongs to the <hi>Second Table,</hi> referring to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Law of our Neighbour; which Law, (as St. <hi>John</hi> expounds it, <hi>cap.</hi> 3. 18.) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in <hi>words alone,</hi> but in <hi>Truth, and real Teſtimonies of Affection.</hi> Who ſhall believe we Love indeed, without appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent works of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity?</hi> The Scripture teacheth us a Method of doing Mercy, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) not talking of it only; for then are acts of <hi>Charity</hi> beſt perform'd, when feweſt words are made of the <hi>Benevolence:</hi> Giving of <hi>Alms,</hi> is at one and the ſame time, to Love <hi>God,</hi> and honour Him in his Image; to make a Friend, and to relieve a Neighbour.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Saviour calleth it, <hi>An evil Generation, who demanded a ſign of their Redemption:</hi> And we cannot Repute it a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35343:15"/>better, that ask, <hi>Where is the Mandate for well doing?</hi> A ſmall excuſe Men are willing to make uſe of, to ſave their Eſtates; and where the Commandment is Poſitive, they ſeek for their own ſakes, (more than their Neighbours,) to dwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the Precept into a Councel: Yet is this more than a meer matter of Advice; for it is a Breviate of what our dear Maſter left us in Charge, at his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; <hi>viz. That we Love one another;</hi> which Love admits of no proof inferior to that of <hi>Almſgiving.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Holy Writ, and all the <hi>Tomes</hi> of the Fathers, abounds with Exhortation to this Duty: But this is added to poor Mens miſeries, they now live in a cold Age of the World; and here, in a very chill Climate. 'Tis a wonder, to hear Men, every where, boaſt of <hi>Faith,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Mercy;</hi> and when they ſhew no fruits of a living <hi>Faith,</hi> ſtill do boaſt of <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> For (<hi>Charitate ipſa, nihil Charius,</hi>) Love, and its Effects, are ſome of our greateſt Rarities.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35343:15"/>
            <p>When we ſpeak of Chriſtians, none can be miſtaken, where we find <hi>Charity,</hi> but the Giver, and he not eaſily; but admitting he may looſe part of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, by valuing his Gift at too great a Rate, or by wronging himſelf, by the manner of Giving; we have a great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that he that pretends to <hi>Faith,</hi> without <hi>Works,</hi> deceives himſelf, and the whole World, and offers to put a Cheat upon his Maſter; for he doth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value, at one and the ſame time, his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Brethren, and the Truth of Divine Promiſes.</p>
            <p>Some tells of three ſorts of <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> that occur in Scripture, <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative, Negative,</hi> and <hi>Mixt:</hi> The <hi>Decalogue</hi> conſiſts of ſuch as are moſtly <hi>Negative,</hi> though ſome of them are <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative;</hi> As, <hi>Keep holy the Sabbath: Honour thy Parents, &amp;c.</hi> And more of that ſort we have in the <hi>Bible;</hi> as, <hi>Mourn for thy Sins; Shew Mercy; Do Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp;c.</hi> There are alſo <hi>Commandments</hi> of a Mixt nature; as of <hi>Reſtoration,</hi> and <hi>Forgiveneſs, &amp;c.</hi> A Negative <hi>Commandment</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35343:16"/>doth oblige all Perſons at all Times, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, and Eternally: <hi>Affirmative</hi> Precepts are binding for ever, but not in all Times, nor in all Places; Mixt <hi>Commandments</hi> oblige us at all Times, and in all Places; but not always.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not determine to which of theſe Sorts the Words of <hi>Solomon</hi> may beſt be reduc'd; but, am certain, they oblige all perſons of Ability, to Confer <hi>Benefits,</hi> and pay <hi>good Offices,</hi> according to their power, to all perſons, without Excuſe or Exemption; that entreat their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſt thy Bread upon the Waters.</hi>] We read it <hi>Caſt</hi> in our Common <hi>Engliſh-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles;</hi> intimating, That if we are oblig'd to <hi>caſt,</hi> or <hi>ſcatter</hi> our <hi>Charity,</hi> we ought not to be very curious in Examining every Circumſtance concerning our <hi>Gift,</hi> and the Conditon of the Receiver; but we ſhould give frequently, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally, without an exceſſive Care to whom, or to what purpoſe our <hi>Donative</hi> is beſtow'd: It is enough, that we know our own Intentions to be Warrantable,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35343:16"/>without ſearching too ſtrickly into the Meaning or Appetite of the Petitioner: Let us not be too ſcrupulous in ſeeking a very fit Object, to make the beſt uſe of what we beſtow; leſt ſuch a ſevere Examination ſhould obſtruct our <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> 'Tis lawful to enquire, but not with too much Curioſity, how the Receiver became Poor; but if he have fail'd in Diligence to Live, let us not fail in his Support, for to ſupply his preſent Want, which is the way to Encourage him to be Diligent for the future: Never let the Deſpicable Circumſtances of any perſon in Deſpair, or any manner of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, divert thy Bounty; It is a Niceneſs <hi>God</hi> cannot approve, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penceth many Mercies to thee, where few are deſerved.</p>
            <p>But if we take it according to that other Reading, and Tranſlate for the word <hi>Caſt,</hi> or <hi>Scatter; Send,</hi> or <hi>Sow;</hi> it implies Caution, and addeth an Act of <hi>Prudence</hi> to that of <hi>Charity:</hi> Then it will import a Care and Art in Giving, as well as in Enjoyment. Where <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35343:17"/>directs us to ſend our <hi>Charity,</hi> he does intend we ſhould give <hi>Alms</hi> with Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and to be Cautious in diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing our Bounty. <hi>Alms</hi> is a ſort of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize that we Barter with Heaven, and which we ought to ſend with Circumſpection, that they may not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry. 'Tis no Wiſe-man's way to be Careleſs of what he ſendeth, but he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits it to the ſureſt Hands, that it may be ſafely conveyed to the Owner: A ſmall Token, a Ring, or a Letter, is not truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with every idle Fellow that is of ſmall Truſt, or no good Reputation; but we make it our Buſineſs, to know from whence the Meſſenger cometh, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he deſigns to Travel, that taketh charge of our meaneſt Preſents. The <hi>Wife-man</hi> here adviſeth us to the ſame Method; ſo to ſend our <hi>Alms</hi> in the ſafeſt Bottoms, and by <hi>God's</hi> uſual Meſſengers, that they may be ſafely deliver'd; not ſuffering our Contributions to Periſh, or ſtrengthen the Hand of the Evil-Doer: We muſt not Give with a Deſign to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote evil Councels, ill Practiſes, or bad
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35343:17"/>Company; leaſt of all, muſt we give to further Laſcivious Courſes, or multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Places of Debauchery: To do this, is not giving <hi>Alms,</hi> but a joyning of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt Heaven, to augment the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the Riotous; whoſe great Work is to maintain Brothels, or repair Houſes of Licentious Entertainment, where <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath no Habitation; ſuch Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence is prejudicial to the Rule, and to the Reward of <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Send thy Bread;]</hi> Sending implies a Communication of the Good Things that are in our Power, to ſuch as live at a Diſtance, as well as to the Neigbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: Let us do good abroad, for that argueth true Devotion at home; not to give only ſo far as our Hand can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, but as far as our Gift can be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the Hands of Others. The <hi>Houſhold of Faith</hi> is firſt to be conſider'd and reliev'd, and what remains is the Portion of diſtreſſed Strangers, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers. I wiſh I could truly ſay, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had not as much need of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as any Nation; I think we have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35343:18"/>been ſo far from approving our ſelves Charitable to Strangers, that we ſcarce afford them Civil uſage. Let us no more pretend to <hi>Science</hi> and <hi>Reformation,</hi> until we ceaſe to be Barbarous, and have learn'd Humanity: What if they be remote? what if they be <hi>Jews?</hi> what if they be <hi>Turks?</hi> what if they be <hi>Pagans?</hi> we muſt not excuſe our ſelves, by pleading Ignorance of their Lineage, their Principles, or their Country: 'tis enough that we know their unfortunate Condition. <hi>Send,</hi> is an <hi>Imperative word,</hi> that leaveth not the Thing Indifferent, or at our Election; but chargeth us to <hi>give Alms,</hi> and <hi>to do good,</hi> according to our Ability, without making abatement for want of Merit in the Receiver; or for the ſake of the ſtrong Averſion we bear to his Perſon, or to his Religion. The word <hi>Send,</hi> declares it a Duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbant, expreſly commanding us to <hi>ſhew Mercy,</hi> without Excuſes, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Delay: If you neglect to beſtow what you can well Spare, 'tis at worſt an Act of Injuſtice, at beſt, a Detinue.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35343:18"/>Send your Charity where you cannot go, for fear of Corporal Danger, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation: it is infamous for ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally to give to ſome people; there you muſt ſend your Charity, where your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to carry it, would bring upon you a Scandal: Shorten not your Hand of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour from the poor Priſoner, that's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt pin'd and ſmoother'd in a noyſom Dungeon. Send your Bounty to the <hi>Sick,</hi> that are going to their <hi>Graves</hi> with ſome Infectious Diſeaſe: You may ſafely ſend it, when you cannot go with ſafety. Yes, and there are ſome Caſes, wherein the <hi>good Chriſtian</hi> muſt hazard <hi>Reputation</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> to perform <hi>good Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices;</hi> that is, where <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Nature,</hi> his <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Country,</hi> are moſt nearly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd: Here it is he muſt Advance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Dangers, ſtruggle with all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, &amp; encounter with evil <hi>Beaſts,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did at <hi>Epheſus:</hi> We muſt fight upon ſuch great Occaſions, an whole Army of <hi>Scandals;</hi> there we muſt not matter Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy, but oppoſe our ſelves to the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranies of <hi>State,</hi> and ſtand the unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35343:19"/>Cenſures of the Inſolent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Multitude. There are Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Counſels that have the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence over <hi>good Men,</hi> as if they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with them the Nature and Force of a Commandment: But theſe words of <hi>Solomon</hi> are a <hi>poſitive Law,</hi> which, not only Invites us to, but Preſcribes us <hi>Obedience.</hi> The Neglect or Omiſſion, to obſerve thoſe Counſels, we read in the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> as, <hi>ſingle Life, voluntary Poverty,</hi> &amp;c. are but Imperfections in our Nature; whereas the Breach of this Law of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> is a plain Sin, a complicated Sin; and of that ſort, that renders the Sinner odious in the higheſt Degree; becauſe there is more comprehended in this Law of <hi>Love,</hi> than in all other Laws, Divine and Humane; for Love is the Life and End of Laws, and this one is the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the <hi>Ten Commandments.</hi> There is nothing enjoyn'd by the <hi>Church,</hi> for Defects in <hi>Alms-giving,</hi> becauſe there it is that God reſerveth the Sentence to Himſelf, and puniſheth the failure in that Duty, with more than the Church is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35343:19"/>willing to Declare: Only God hath been pleas'd to Reveal how far <hi>good Works</hi> are acceptable to him, and what Happineſs <hi>they</hi> will procure for us hereafter, that He may ſee how far we are willing to proceed in our Charity, for the ſake of Divine Love, and for an Eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Send your <hi>Alms</hi> therefore as far as <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Silas,</hi> Camels, or Ships will carry them; from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Macedon,</hi> or <hi>Antioch;</hi> or from the place of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> or <hi>Hungary:</hi> To this end we were indued with reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Faculties, with the Comforts of this Life, and all thoſe Temporal Bleſſings that are reacht within the Complicated Name of an <hi>Eſtate;</hi> that we might Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our <hi>God</hi> in Compliance with his <hi>holy Will;</hi> and that we might enjoy and benefit our ſelves and others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Send thy Bread.]</hi> Bread is of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Uſe, and large Extent; ſignifying all that is neceſſary for Man's Subſiſtence: All manner of Proviſion is included in that <hi>Monoſyllable.</hi> The <hi>Chaldee. Dialect</hi> expreſſeth a <hi>Sumptuous Feaſt,</hi> by the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35343:20"/>word, <hi>Bread</hi> delighting to ſet forth a large Bill of <hi>Fare</hi> in a few Letters, and with a ſingle word, to furniſh a Table more for Pleaſure than Neceſſity. And this luxurious Senſe, the word <hi>Bread</hi> carries, <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 10.19. For which cauſe ſome inform us, the <hi>Grecians</hi> derived the word [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] that ſignifies every Thing: and their God <hi>Pan,</hi> from <hi>Panis,</hi> that goeth for Bread among the <hi>Latins;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the Dearth of Fleſh, Wine or Oyls, but the want of Bread alone, ſtyled a <hi>Famine</hi> in Scripture. Bread is termed the <hi>Staff of Life,</hi> that ſupports the <hi>Feeble,</hi> (<hi>Pſalm</hi> 104.) And, <hi>fulneſs of Bread,</hi> was ever reputed one of the greateſt Bleſſings of the <hi>Jewiſh Nation;</hi> the Plenty thereof prevents Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for ſuch as follow'd Chriſt, chiefly for the ſake of the <hi>Loaves</hi> and <hi>Fiſhes;</hi> more for the Miracles he wrought, to <hi>feed them,</hi> and <hi>heal them,</hi> than for the ſake of his Prayers, or his Preaching. The Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, (I mean thoſe that are ready to make their Belly their God,) are moſt Devout there, where they can find moſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35343:20"/>Bread, and care not to embrace a Religion that commends Faſting: remove their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, ſet aſide their Biſhops, take away their Prieſts, and their Chriſt too, you provoke them not much, ſo as you leave them entire, their Wine and their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet. Our ordinary Prayer, is for <hi>daily Bread,</hi> with which every one of us ought to reſt contented, is the one thing neceſſary, if it be taken for our common Proviſion; but it is <hi>the only thing neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary,</hi> if taken as divers excellent Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Dr. <hi>Perſon</hi> upon the <hi>Creed,</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, <hi>The Divine Food of our Souls,</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed Sacrament.</hi> The <hi>Roman Satyriſt</hi> knew how much the People va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu'd Bread, while he informs us, they covet nothing above [<hi>Panem &amp; circen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>] Bread and Recreation; meaning by the Firſt of the Two, <hi>all neceſſary Proviſion.</hi> [<hi>Caſt thy Bread;</hi>] that is, thy Subſtance or Eſtate, thy Means of Living; or whatever a Man needeth: If it be dear to thee, it will be dearer to thy <hi>God;</hi> who when you eſteem it not much, values it as little. He was no leſs
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35343:21"/>than a Royal Divine, that uſeth this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; <hi>Shall I give to God that which coſteth me nothing?</hi> The Poor are God's Receivers, and his Factors; if you have Ability to Diſpence much to them for his Service, and to ſend great Things by their Hands, you ſhall be certain of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Returns. That is not to be called <hi>Charity,</hi> but ridding of your Houſe, to beſtow ſome pitiful thing upon the Poor, that other-ways to keep, would diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage their Maſter. How can Men expect their Reward to be Great, where they place a matter of ſo ſmall Merit? <hi>Bread,</hi> implies ſomething that is good, and ſome-what in readineſs; to ſhew you, that you are to Give with Expedition, that which may prove beneficial to the Petitioner: That which you beſtow, ought to be wholſome, or advantageous, conducing to the Health or Profit of the Receiver: You are not ſo much to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect his Pleaſure; though in ſome Caſes of Deſpair or Sickneſs, that is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to be neglected. Let your <hi>Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> be ſuch as Nature requireth, rather
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35343:21"/>than a Banquet, or piece of Rarity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſt,</hi> or <hi>Send thy Bread;</hi> give the ſame in Subſtance or in Quality, with which Thou doſt uſually furniſh thy own Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: So 'tis in the <hi>Chaldee, Spare from thy own Mouth the Bread of thy Table:</hi> For this end did the <hi>Church</hi> anciently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point frequent Faſts, that the Proviſion which was ſpar'd by good Mens Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, might ſupply the Wants of thoſe that groan'd in Poverty.</p>
            <p>Thus by feeding the Mouths of the Hungry, thou doſt engage the Tongues of the needy Beads-man, to make Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Interceſſions for Thee at the Throne of Mercy, praiſing God for thy ſake, the Author of all Good to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and by their Importunate Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>taking Heaven by violence,</hi> and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down Bleſſings upon Thee and thy Family.</p>
            <p>It was thus our Fore-fathers; thus the firſt and beſt Chriſtians Faſted, giving thoſe Diſhes of Meat to the Poor, which themſelves ſhould have eaten. But now, [<hi>Terras aſtrâ reliquit;</hi>] Devotion is fled,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35343:22"/>and too many, not only devour the Meat &amp; Subſiſtance of the Poor, but the poor Men too; while any thing given to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Uſes, is interpreted with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to Feaſt Pariſh-Officers. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may we ſee Fatted daily with Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Surfeited with Exceedings; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Poor with nothing, or that which their Dogs would refuſe; delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more in Foddering their Beaſts, than Relieving their hungry Brethren; and to feed Hogs, or Hounds, are Covetous to pine helpleſs Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>I hope in all this there is but little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; to let the poor Man want Bread for his Family, while a Rich Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire perhaps uſurps the <hi>Owners Living;</hi> driving out poor <hi>Chriſtians</hi> from their <hi>own Habitations,</hi> to keep Hawks, and Whores, and Hounds, in their Abodes: You cannot imagine it is this <hi>Solomon</hi> means, when he ſays; <hi>Caſt thy Bread upon the Waters.</hi> Bread is a cheap and ready thing to beſtow; you need not go far to porcure ſuch an Alms for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Petitioner.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:35343:22"/>
            <p>This Imports, that we muſt not ſerve the Poor with Delays, but make Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches in our Charity; becauſe, what we are to give is ready; there is no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for us to go to <hi>Burdeaux</hi> for Wines, or to <hi>Virginia</hi> for Smoak; or to fetch <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Silks, or Import <hi>Perſian</hi> Tapſteries, in order to perform Works of Mercy: Give your <hi>Bread,</hi> that is neither Dear to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, nor difficult to procure. What ſhould they, poor Hearts, that ſtand wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for your Alms, do with uſeleſs Toys, or extravagant Curioſities? 'Tis no Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to beſtow a Thing that is vain, or ſuperfluous, tending more to Man's Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, than Profit. You may Give and Debauch, as well as Give and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; 'tis <hi>Bread,</hi> not Bottles of <hi>Brumſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> or <hi>Canary,</hi> that are required; What is it you can more eaſily reach, or forgo? Yet is this <hi>Bread</hi> more acceptable to the <hi>hungry Soul,</hi> than <hi>Ingots</hi> of Gold in a Wilderneſs, or a Palace of Ivory. If the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> did not take too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Truſt, thoſe <hi>Aegyptian-Children</hi> that were ſuckled by <hi>Goats,</hi> and not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35343:23"/>to hear any Humane Speech, were taught by Nature to pronounce the word <hi>Beccos,</hi> that ſignifies <hi>Bread</hi> in the <hi>Coptick</hi> Language: But if the truth of this Report faileth; 'tis certain, our Lamp of Light, [<hi>Byolychimum;</hi>] by which we live, and move, and make ſuch a Figure as we have, ſubſiſteth not, but by daily ſupplys of ſome proper Oily Nutriment: and Nature cannot be ſo far wanting to Her-ſelf, and to Us, as not to ſeek and demand (after her own way) ſomewhat of Subſiſtence to preſerve that Vital Flame from ſinking in the Lamp, or in the Heart, its Receptacle, from a dark Extinction.</p>
            <p>[<hi>Caſt thy Bread.</hi>] The Bread thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt muſt be thine; it ought to be ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with the Character of <hi>Property;</hi> let it be thine by ſome known right, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſputable Poſſeſſion: Thine lawfully, not obtained by Fraud, or Violence. He that <hi>grindeth the Face of the Poor,</hi> to feed an <hi>Hoſpital</hi> with the Bread of ſuch Get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings: He that purveys, purloins, and pilfers, and out of much, ſo gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35343:23"/>thinks to diſtribute a little, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing now and then ſome ſmall <hi>Alms</hi> for Oſtentation, doth an iller thing, than the Man that ſtealeth a <hi>Gooſe,</hi> to ſtick a <hi>Feather:</hi> for, to leſſen a Levy for the Poor, he puts a ſcorn upon all obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Nature; and to open himſelf a way to the Name of Riches, he forceth a breach in the Law of Nations; ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to himſelf not to ſhew a Bounty, that ſhall exceed noiſe and appearance, he falleth under thoſe Curſes, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly purſue Covetous and unjuſt Wretches. Not much inferior in doing wrong, is he, that oweth all he beſtows, and meaneth not otherwiſe to diſcharge his Debts in this World, than by making God (by giving to the Poor) Truſtee for ballancing his preſent Account, and his Debtor, to make good his future Eſtate: This is not to be truly Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, out of his own, (as every man ought to be,) but out of his Creditors Coffers; and ſeeming to be Zealous for God, he wrongeth his Friend that lends or forbears the Charity he makes bold
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35343:24"/>to diſpoſe: Nor is it a ſingle Injury; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in ſuch acts, he doth prejudice to Human Society, that is beſt preſerved by juſt and punctual Dealing: Have we not thoſe among us, that by Wit and Deceit, live out one half of the year, exerciſing them both in Worldly matters? and the other half, they wear out much in the ſame manner, with ſpecious pretences of Law, and Religious Hypocriſie; they walk with their Eyes lifted up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and would have all others do ſo too, that they may not be able to diſcern the Lands and Tenements they have ſeized upon Earth, by the Arts of Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>Such as can Uſurp Lordſhips under a Pretext of Law, and take Sanctuary in a Church, while they Rob the Hoſpital, ſhall They hope to expiate their Sins by ſome ſmall Contributions? or to eſcape the Torments of Hell, by leaving at their Death ſome ſmall Legacy to the Poor of the Pariſh? Their hopes are vain and dangerous, that hope by Building an Alms-houſe, to obtain a Licenſe from Heaven, for the Uſurpation of a Lordſhip;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35343:24"/>what is this, but to render our ſelves Slaves to the Prince of Darkneſs, and Enemies to good and honeſt Men, all our lives; only with hopes of ſerving God a little at our Death, and of doing ſome good, it may be an hour before our Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals? Let all good Men rather believe, that Shame and Confuſion, and horrid Spectres, attend the Tombs of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Perſons! and that the Houſes, from which thoſe miſerable Wretches are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd, (when Life and Sin forſakes them) ſhall be daily Beſieg'd with the Cries of Widows and Orphans, and with the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of all thoſe diſtreſſed Creatures that were undone, and made pitiful objects of Charity, by the power and artifices of thoſe Ill-livers; and that thoſe Manſions of theirs (if there be left one Stone upon another) ſhall remain upon Earth, but as execrable Monuments of their Impiety. Suppoſing there were none of theſe, yet to defer our Charity till Death, is to loſe much of the commendation that is inſeparable from holy Practiſes; becauſe then it appears a work of neceſſity, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35343:25"/>give that away, which we cannot longer poſſeſs: ſure it is not a very deſerving matter, for me to pretend to relieve or gratify ſome perſon with that thing, which refuſeth any more to own me for its Maſter. Thus Divines love to ſpeak, that they may quicken Charitable minds, to call down Bleſſings betimes upon themſelves, and their Poſterity; to ſecure their Eſtates to their Iſſue, by giving Alms according to their Power; and that the beſt Chriſtians may thereby feel and acknowledge the reward of good Works, before they change their condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Send thy Bread.</hi>] Thou haſt no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to diſpoſe, (under the notion of thy own,) of the Bread of the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Buyer, or the defrauded Labourer; leaſt of all muſt you beſtow the Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread, or that which hath been Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly taken from God's own Table; but ſend the Bread that is lawfully thine, by juſt Title and harmleſs Poſſeſſion; if not thine by Inheritance, yet thine by Gift, Purchaſe, or Labour; thine by ſome honeſt way of Trading or Deſert; thine
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35343:25"/>by lawful Arts, or laudable Induſtry: Whoſoever giveth Alms of ill gotten Goods, doth worſe than the Fellow that offer'd a Sow to <hi>Pallas:</hi> 'Tis a great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front that he doth to the Deity, offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>GOD</hi> that which is more loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to Him, than Swines Blood, the price of a Dog, or the hire of an Harlot: <hi>He Killeth the Son, before the Father's Face,</hi> ſays the Wiſdom of <hi>Sirach: Eccleſ.</hi> 34. 20. <hi>He Selleth</hi> Joſeph <hi>his Brother, that he may carry home a Coat to his Sier.</hi> I wiſh there were fewer of thoſe Men in this Age, who being Honoured with the Bleſſing of a plentiful Eſtate, are yet Covetous to become the Executors of their pooreſt Neighbours; making daily Merchandize with the <hi>Beggar's<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Penny,</hi> ſelling the Sweat of the Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Brows, his ſingle Beaſt, or little Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; and when they have given them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Poſſeſſion of all the ſmall <hi>Pittance</hi> he has, they continue to force him into deſperate Extremities. This is not to <hi>Caſt thy Bread upon the Waters;</hi> but to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35343:26"/>caſt thy ſelf backward, to Worſhip the <hi>Tempter,</hi> and gratifie him with thy Fall and Degradation.</p>
            <p>'Tis no better, to cozen all the Week in the Shop, that you may give <hi>Alms</hi> on the Lord's-Day; or to Impoveriſh as many as poſſibly you can, in your whole Life, only to leave behind ſome ſmall Relict of an Eſtate [<hi>when you Die,</hi>] either to Feaſt the Pariſh, or Repair the Church, or Adorn it, as ſome (not of the better ſort of Chriſtians) fancy'd they did, by placing a <hi>Cheap-Figure</hi> of the Serpent upon the Steeple.</p>
            <p>The Wicked Man's Legacy to the Poor, when this World will continue no longer with him, is no <hi>Charity,</hi> but a ſort of Reſtitution; which cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce its proper Effect, becauſe it is not performed to the right Party. Let that therefore be thine, that thou giveſt away, that thy <hi>Alms</hi> may be more acceptable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſt thy Bread upon the Waters.</hi>] We may underſtand by theſe <hi>Waters,</hi> all thoſe that are moſt ſubject to <hi>Tears,</hi> the <hi>Sick</hi> and <hi>Friendleſs,</hi> and ſuch as are any
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35343:26"/>way brought into <hi>Diſtreſs:</hi> The <hi>Stranger,</hi> the <hi>Widow,</hi> and <hi>Fatherleſs,</hi> that go hand in hand, throughout the Scripture.</p>
            <p>All thoſe ſad objects of <hi>Pity,</hi> that are not only ſent into this World, to ſhew what the Lord is able to do, but alſo, what Fleſh and Blood deſerves to ſuffer, (and more than that, to make Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what Men are willing to do for <hi>GOD,</hi> our great Benefactor) are ſent hither to be <hi>Receivers</hi> of our <hi>Charity:</hi> You may read their <hi>Errand</hi> in their Faces, and their <hi>Commiſſion</hi> in Scripture; where <hi>GOD</hi> paſſeth His Word for the Foundation of the Charitable Man's Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and gives His <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> to be <hi>Security</hi> for your <hi>Repayment:</hi> 'Tis this Infallible <hi>Word of God,</hi> upon which you put the <hi>Adventure;</hi> theſe <hi>Waters</hi> would deceive you, without that <hi>Word's</hi> Aſſurance: For, what <hi>Recompence</hi> can you expect from the meaneſt Abject, from ſuch as are loaded with this World's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, with Loſſes, or with Nature's Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections?</p>
            <p>'Tis the way of many of thoſe that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35343:27"/>ſtand upon good Bottoms (as to this Life) to make uſe of the Times, and of all Expedients, to Advance or Secure their Fortunes, to Court thoſe that are in high Places, and Flatter ſuch as are in Authority; whereas <hi>GOD</hi> giveth us an Original of another nature, <hi>Exalting the Humble, and Filling the Hungry, while the Rich are ſent away Empty;</hi> not out of Hatred to their Perſons, but becauſe He hath already conferred upon them extraordinary Favours, and rendered them (before) remarkable Objects of his Bounty; thoſe <hi>Waters</hi> are Fluxive and Inconſtant: Court the <hi>Waves,</hi> and they will Drown you for your Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Yes, and much like that, is the Temper of the pooreſt ſort of People; <hi>Give</hi> them, and they will throw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon you, and throw Dirt in your Face; yet their Aſperſions ſhall but add weight to their own <hi>Sorrow,</hi> and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Waters</hi> you <hi>Feed,</hi> ſhall threaten your <hi>Ruine</hi> with their raging Motions and Inconſtancy; yet the Command
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35343:27"/>runs, you muſt <hi>Feed</hi> theſe <hi>Waters,</hi> tho' it is the Nature of them to let the <hi>Benefit</hi> ſink and diſappear: Fear not, it is in their Will, but not in their Power, either to <hi>hide</hi> or to <hi>drown</hi> your works of <hi>Mercy:</hi> And, for your Incouragement, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber theſe <hi>Waters,</hi> even the pooreſt <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals</hi> are made for your <hi>Eaſe,</hi> your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> and your <hi>Advantage;</hi> make it your buſineſs to imploy them in the beſt manner: Theſe <hi>Waters</hi> will do you good, if you underſtand their Uſes; there is a way for you to be <hi>Charitable to the Poor,</hi> and at the ſame time receive profit by their Service. It is an <hi>Element</hi> that is an uſeful part of the World; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Poor,</hi> the <hi>Rich</hi> knows not how to Subſiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Livy,</hi> long ago, made <hi>Three</hi> ſorts of Men, and his diviſion is thus far verify'd; there has always been a <hi>Governing</hi> part, and a <hi>Teaching</hi> part among Men; and there is a <hi>Third</hi> ſort, that ſeem to have been Born meerly for <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi> He that hath his Talent in his <hi>Head,</hi> or in his <hi>Coffer,</hi> muſt imploy ſuch
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35343:28"/>as have it in their <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Feet;</hi> by which, they may ſerve themſelves with the juſt and neceſſary Comforts of this Life, and, at the ſame time, prove <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſt thy Bread upon the</hi> Waters.] intimating, we are obliged to do <hi>Good,</hi> without <hi>Grudging,</hi> as if what thou <hi>Giveſt</hi> were to Periſh; not looking to perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate thy Name, or obtain a preſent Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe; not expecting ſo much as a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal Recompence from the <hi>Receiver.</hi> Write upon the <hi>Sea,</hi> with the beſt of Pencils, and a Man of exquiſite Sight ſhall not find there one legible Character: No more ſhould we perform acts of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> for Sight or Oſtentation; becauſe the <hi>Good Works</hi> that are moſt <hi>ſecretly</hi> carried, ſhall be moſt, and moſt <hi>openly</hi> Rewarded; yet there is a Time, when <hi>Good Works</hi> ought to be <hi>Viſible,</hi> and ſo to be Tranſacted, that they may be diſcern'd:</p>
            <p n="1">1. For <hi>Diſtinction,</hi> that a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may be ſignaliz'd by his <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:35343:28"/>of others; ſuch Lights are now a days wanting, to thoſe that are miſled in the ways of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>GOD</hi> hath ſo ordered his Bleſſings, that many times <hi>viſible Good Works,</hi> and <hi>publick Rewards</hi> meet, and are as the noiſe of ſo many <hi>Waters:</hi> The flux, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux, and freedom of Motion in that <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> teacheth us to multiply <hi>Good Works,</hi> and give <hi>Alms</hi> Liberally: The Lord loveth the <hi>Chearful Giver,</hi> whoſe Acts of <hi>Charity</hi> reſemble the <hi>Waves</hi> rolling one upon another.</p>
            <p>Whoever communicates his <hi>Bread unwillingly,</hi> more to deliver himſelf from the Petitioner's Importunity, than for the ſake of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or in obedience to his Commands; that Man, ſurely, either diſtruſts <hi>GOD's Knowledge,</hi> or his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> imagining his Maſter is ignorant of his <hi>Eſtate,</hi> or his <hi>Meaning;</hi> or he dares not truſt Him, to requite his <hi>Kindneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will you hear another Reaſon, that may prevail with us to <hi>Caſt our Bread upon the Waters;</hi> It is, becauſe thoſe <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> by their ſeveral Channels, return
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35343:29"/>to their <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Fountain. CHRIST</hi> is that <hi>Head, Source,</hi> or <hi>Spring</hi> of thoſe <hi>Waters,</hi> on which our <hi>Bread</hi> is to be ſcatter'd. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſtiled <hi>Shiloh</hi> in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bibles, ſignifying a <hi>Fountain of living Waters:</hi> The <hi>Poor</hi> ſtream from Him; and, by them, our <hi>Charity</hi> ſhall ſuddenly be return'd into <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Boſom: For this, among other Reaſons, our <hi>Shiloh,</hi> the Saviour of the World, did appear Poor, and deſtitute of Friends, and Temperal Comforts, to promote, and to make Tryal of the World's <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Care is to be taken, that the Frowns of the <hi>Alms-giver</hi> may not ſowre the <hi>Bread</hi> he beſtows; but let a liberal hand, and a chearful Heart, accompany'd with Affability, render the Gift more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging, and the Gratuity more valuable; ſo will your Kindneſs every where be welcome; ſo will it be manifeſt, you <hi>Give</hi> for the Love of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and not meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in hopes of a Requital: <hi>He that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Mercy, let him do it with Chearfulneſs,</hi> ſays the great Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles, Rom.</hi> 12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 7. From ſuch a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35343:29"/>Mind proceeds the Name of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality,</hi> ſays <hi>Seneca,</hi> in his Tract of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits;</hi> whoſe Sentences, more than Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, ſeem Abſtracts of that Evangelical Doctrine, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> Taught the <hi>Romans,</hi> to whom <hi>Seneca</hi> was a Friend, and ſome think a Diſciple: Thoſe <hi>Gifts</hi> are leſs acceptable that caſually fall, or have been extorted by vehement en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties; but of the Two, the firſt are moſt grateful; that is, where a Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that was deſign'd for one Party, happens, againſt the Will of the <hi>Donor,</hi> to be the Lot of another; which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cometh to paſs, through a miſtake, by our particular Providence.</p>
            <p>A good Chriſtian will approve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf habitually Kind; and he will, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Mind, always remain <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</hi> This readineſs to <hi>Give,</hi> is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to Heaven, as much as to the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Receiver; whoſe deſire is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, altho' his Demands are, by the greateſt expedition that can be uſed in diſpenſing your Bounty: ('tis in theſe caſes, that ſpeedy Help is double Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35343:30"/>
               <hi>Multaque gratius venit quod facili, quam quod plena manu datur.</hi>) It matters not, whether the Hand be <hi>full,</hi> ſo as it be <hi>ready</hi> to communicate.</p>
            <p>The Perſon that doubts or delays to relieve the <hi>Poor,</hi> ſhews ſome unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and while he taketh time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the caſe, and defers his Anſwer, by cauſing the Petitioner too long to wait upon his Pleaſure, he ſpoyls the <hi>Benefit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Go, and come again to Morrow,</hi> are the words of no good Chriſtian, and but of an ill Neighbour: 'Tis a ſubtle ſort of Denial, that proves the more cruel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is Politick. I would chuſe rather to refuſe the <hi>Mendicant's</hi> Requeſt at once, than twice to Anſwer him coldly; ſo as my delays, by tyring the poor Creatures Patience, ſhall force him to ſeek that Aſſiſtance from others, which is in my Power to contribute. Such is the ſpiritual Nature of all Works of Mercy, they are apt to evaporate by ſlow effuſions; whereas he that ſuddenly <hi>Giveth,</hi> by ſhortning the Time, doubles the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver's Profit. You cannot be delighted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35343:30"/>with the Sighs, Groans, and Tears of Chriſtians, almoſt Pin'd and Naked; Muſt the ſorrowful Accents of the Poor, awaken your dull <hi>Charity?</hi> Then ſuppoſe your ſelf as much in Want, and as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate, imploring at the Gate of <hi>Heaven,</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> for Mercy; then imagine an Angry Judge delaying to give Ear to your Complaints: Why ſhould not that <hi>GOD</hi> you have ſo much, and often Offended, uſe you with the ſame vigour, and examine you with the ſame ſtrictneſs? Why ſhould he not hear, before your Face, ill Neighbours accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing you with Violence and Falſhood; ſcarce permitting you to plead in your own defence? Why ſhould he not take all advantage of your Pleading? This is your way; and therefore, no more than in Juſtice you ought to expect. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear your hopes of Mercy, after your Death, which in your Life you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to extend to your afflicted Brother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſt thy Bread upon the</hi> Waters.] Remember it is an Element of Univerſal uſe, in which all plead a freedom; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35343:31"/>for the Benefit of all Creatures; and ſuch is the nature of <hi>Charity;</hi> 'Tis univerſally communicable, and ought to be every where flowing. We are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd, not only to <hi>Give,</hi> but to <hi>Give</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally, without reſpecting the Perſon, or enquiring too ſeverely into the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or other circumſtances of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay: Hear Saint <hi>Paul</hi> publiſhing this Doctrine, <hi>Gal. 6. Do good unto all Men:</hi> 'Tis a general Rule, without exception; yet there is a Remark follows in the <hi>Tenth</hi> Verſe of that Chapter, <hi>That it ought to be done to the Houſhold of Faith eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially;</hi> directing our <hi>Alms</hi> to be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted in a more particular manner to ſome, than to others.</p>
            <p>Receive the Rule therefore in this Senſe, <hi>Do good to All,</hi> but to ſome more eminently; <hi>Give there,</hi> and <hi>Give yonder,</hi> but <hi>Give here</hi> more plentifully; <hi>Allow</hi> them, but <hi>Maintain</hi> theſe; there <hi>Relieve,</hi> but here <hi>Support:</hi> You muſt look upon the <hi>Houſhold of Faith</hi> as your own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, that calls for your Paternal Care and Conduct, as the Neighbourhood does for your Kindneſs.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:35343:31"/>
            <p>The beſt next, are thoſe good Offices ſhewed to your Country: Then all Men, and the whole World of <hi>Pagans,</hi> ſo far as they Want, and you are able to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, are become Objects of your <hi>Charity:</hi> For all good Chriſtians are ſo far from wiſhing, and ſo much further from endeavouring the Confuſion of any Perſon, that they make it their daily buſineſs; not only to pray for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of All, but uſeth all Means, at all Times, to benefit their Souls with their Bodies.</p>
            <p>Truly, that Mandate for <hi>Alms</hi> is very large, St. <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 30. <hi>Give to every Man that asketh,</hi> &amp;c. and He that Impoſeth that Command, is Lord of all that we Poſſeſs: And that we may afford ſo to <hi>Give,</hi> He hath made us as large a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, St. <hi>Matthew 7. Ask, and you ſhall have; Seek, and you ſhall find,</hi> &amp;c. St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> with an Eye upon theſe words of our Bleſſed Saviour, ſays, <hi>We muſt do Good without Diſcretion;</hi> not <hi>Setting,</hi> but <hi>Sowing;</hi> not <hi>Planting,</hi> but <hi>Scattering</hi> our Acts of <hi>Charity;</hi> not uſing too much
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35343:32"/>
               <hi>Exactneſs,</hi> but all manner of <hi>Freedom</hi> in <hi>Giving;</hi> ſo ſhall we reconcile to our ſelves a multitude of Bleſſings. Thus are we encouraged by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Bleſſed are you that Sow beſide all Waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Evangelical <hi>Seer</hi> herein imitates the Language of <hi>Solomon, Caſt thy Bread upon the Waters,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ben. Sira,</hi> varies the Phraſe, ſaying, <hi>Scatter thy Bread upon the Waters, and upon firm Land alſo:</hi> By <hi>Firm Land,</hi> he means Men of Eſtates, Men that are in no Want, as Magiſtrates, and Temporal Powers, (they are the <hi>Terra ſirma,</hi>) and the Rule is, to make this Commandment of <hi>Charity</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to that great Duty of <hi>Obedience,</hi> to which the <hi>Jews,</hi> as well as we, had enough to be Exhorted; that their Man of <hi>Iſrael</hi> deſir'd ſhould include all ſort of Allegiance, which is a Debt of the Subject, to the Supream Power of the Nation; but becauſe this is a <hi>Tiffany</hi> piece, that will abide but gentle touches. I ſhall leave the <hi>Rabbi</hi> to mannage his own Argument: 'Tis certain, <hi>Love</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all that we owe to Superiors,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35343:32"/>as well as Inferiors; and we ought to Obey the Higher Powers; more for Conſcience ſake, than Terror.</p>
            <p>This is the meaning of thoſe Doctors, that tell us, <hi>Dominion is founded in Love, and that by Love, the World is Govern'd:</hi> But, while I am diſcourſing of <hi>Alms,</hi> I ſhall confine the Words of <hi>Solomon</hi> to a more narrow Signification: And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the notion of the <hi>Rabbi,</hi> ſide with that of the Philoſopher, <hi>Vbiamque homo beneficio eſt locus;</hi> Where-ever a Man is, there's place for a Benefit; for where there is a Man, there is Miſery; which, as ſoon as he declares, we are oblig'd to ſhew him Mercy. When the Poor Man ſtandeth at thy door, in expectation of thy Kindneſs, be careful your Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Perſon, his Parentage, his Education, his Country, his manner of Living, be not over tedious or detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental; not made to protract Time, or find Excuſes, or that you may take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Denial: Yet you may lawfully queſtion the Party concern'd, as the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners did <hi>Jonah; Who art thou? Where</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:35343:33"/>
               <hi>is thy Habitation? What's your Imploy?</hi> Not as a News-monger, or one fond of Idle Stories; but as a good Chriſtian, to diſcourage Idleneſs, and promote Piety: Not looking for eminent Vertues in the Beggar, nor demanding large Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials; as if you were to beſtow an Office, or bequeath him your Eſtate; as if you were not then deſign'd to relieve his preſent Wants, but to reward his Merits: Enquire only for <hi>God's-ſake,</hi> and Give for <hi>God's-ſake,</hi> from <hi>GOD</hi> alone expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Recompence.</p>
            <p>What if theſe <hi>Waters</hi> are many? What if they riſe higher and higher upon our Practice? Fear not the failure of your Eſtate, becauſe the Sacrifices are frequent and numerous; becauſe <hi>Alms</hi> is derived from the Corruption of the <hi>Greek, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emoſynary,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] whoſe Root is Mercy, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] of which <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Fountain, and that Fountain is inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible: Yet there is a Barbarous Author, derives <hi>Elemoſynary,</hi> from two words of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> viz. <hi>Eli, God;</hi> and <hi>Mois, Water;</hi> and to confirm his Derivation,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35343:33"/>He ſtileth <hi>Alms,</hi> the <hi>Dew of Heaven.</hi> The Gentleman ſeemeth to have been no great Proficient either in <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Hebrew;</hi> for He might have taken his <hi>Etymology,</hi> with as great Reaſon, from <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Moſes;</hi> and from that infer'd, <hi>Charity</hi> comprehends the <hi>Whole Law,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, leaving <hi>Etymologies, Alms</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined a work of Mercy, Love, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, perſormed only for <hi>GOD's</hi> ſake, to ſome neceſſitated Perſons. In the Work, there is to be conſidered ſomewhat within us [<hi>aliquid intus</hi>] ſo as, looking at home, we find it a Chriſtian Act of <hi>Mercy;</hi> but if we look abroad, it appears an external Act of <hi>Charity,</hi> that is exerted in Obedience to the Divine <hi>Commandment:</hi> We make it a Beauty, by putting upon it the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Face of <hi>Liberality:</hi> 'Tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by Compaſſion; but <hi>Love</hi> gives it the hand of Accompliſhment. A Bountiful Hand and Heart, oblige even thoſe that Hate you, by making their Favours Publick; and, by this happy
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35343:34"/>way of doing well, bribe their Enemies into good Nature.</p>
            <p>If you deſire to ſee the Mother of <hi>Alms,</hi> let me tell you, firſt, if ſhe could appear in Human Shape, nothing but <hi>Truth</hi> could vye Beauty with her; for her Name is <hi>Charity:</hi> She is ſpotted with Stars, and ſpangled with Divine Graces. Here give me leave to ſay, That <hi>Alms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> is a good Work, and is Meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but the Merit is not plac'd upon the bare human Act, but upon the Grace of <hi>GOD's</hi> Holy Spirit, and upon his never-failing Promiſe, which are the Grounds, and conſtitutive Principles of all Merit. 'Tis not us, but the <hi>Grace of</hi> God <hi>working in us,</hi> and the Third Perſon of the Holy Trinity, co-operates with us, that deſerves <hi>GOD</hi>'s Notice, and his Recompenſe, [<hi>Principia meritorum omnium ſunt Divina:</hi>] Yet not excluding the Will and Diſpoſition of the <hi>Alms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver,</hi> that hath the Honour, in all good Works, to co-operate with his Maker. <hi>GOD is Love;</hi> and all Works of Love, partake ſo much of the Divine Nature,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35343:34"/>that they muſt needs be Crowned. But this Diſcourſe relates to the <hi>Promiſe;</hi> yet we were Treating of the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which injoyns us to <hi>Give;</hi> weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Receiver</hi>'s Wants, but over-look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Deſerts; for we are not bidden to Taſte thoſe <hi>Waters,</hi> that we are to caſt our <hi>Bread upon,</hi> to prove, whether they are Sweet or Bitter; for, who-ever giveth <hi>Alms,</hi> not becauſe <hi>GOD</hi> hath ſo Commanded, but becauſe he ſuppoſeth either the Poor have Merited ſo much at his hands already, or now do, or will hereafter deſerve his <hi>Charity;</hi> that Perſon, to ſpeak properly, giveth not an <hi>Alms,</hi> but diſchargeth the Debt, and ſtateth an Account. So he that giveth not meerly for the Lord's-ſake, but in hopes of ſome Human Requital, inſtead of beſtowing his <hi>Alms,</hi> he purchaſeth a <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> and maketh himſelf an Intereſt. The eſpecial attract of <hi>Alms,</hi> ought to be Divine Love, without any by-reſpect to Temporal Returns, or the Merits of the Receiver.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:35343:35"/>
            <p>Why ſhould I tyre you with Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions? Effects of Love ought to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd only to ſuch as are really Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated; for Want is the proper Object of Mercy. Where there is no Want, there may be Favours, Gifts, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, but no perfect <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far in reference to the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The Diviſion of <hi>Alms</hi> hath anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently been in Seven Spiritual Acts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the Soul:
<list>
                  <item>1. To Pray for.</item>
                  <item>2. To Forgive.</item>
                  <item>3. To Admoniſh.</item>
                  <item>4. To Inſtruct.</item>
                  <item>5. To Counſel.</item>
                  <item>6. To Comfort: And,</item>
                  <item>7. To Forbear.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And in Seven more, as pertinent to the Body.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>To Feed the Hungry, and give Drink to the Thirſty;</hi> which ſome divide, and make Two different Offices;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35343:35"/>but I take it as one and the ſame Act of Benevolence, putting in the ſecond place, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Aſſiſtance, or Protection of the Weak, from Bodily Dangers.</item>
               <item>3. To Cloath the Naked.</item>
               <item>4. To Lodge the Harbourleſs.</item>
               <item>5. To Viſit the Sick.</item>
               <item>6. To Bury the Dead: <hi>And,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. To Redeem the Captive, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe are principal Acts of <hi>Charity,</hi> which affords us a mighty Proſpect into a large Field of Diſcourſe, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what beſide our preſent buſineſs: I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire only to lead you to this Duty; to that end, ſetting before you, how much good thoſe beſt of Men, that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, have perform'd for our Example: If we look no farther than the <hi>Jews,</hi> (<hi>GOD</hi>'s Select People) they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd every Third Year, <hi>To Tythe the encreaſe of their Lands a Second Time, for Charitable Uſes,</hi> (after they had Tythed it once for the maintenance of the Clergy:) So we read, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35343:36"/>They gave a Tythe extraordinary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for an <hi>Alms,</hi> to Four ſorts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:
<list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>Stranger.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Fatherleſs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The <hi>Widow:</hi> And,</item>
                  <item>4. The <hi>Poor Infirm Levite,</hi> that could not Officiate.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And in Harveſt, they were forbidden the Reaping every Corner of their Fields, and might not gather up the Gleanings: They were not permitted to pull every Cluſter of Grapes in their <hi>Vintage:</hi> Nor to beat every Bough of their <hi>Olives:</hi> Nor to fetch a Sheaf forgotten.</p>
            <p>Theſe were <hi>Elemoſynary</hi> parcels, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for the Relief of all that were Poor and Afflicted. Theſe Statures are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. 23. And the ſame Commands, and Prohibitions, we find <hi>Deut.</hi> 24. rendring this ſingle, as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, <hi>I am the Lord, your God;</hi> which adds force to the Mandate, and puts a period to the <hi>Duty:</hi> as if the <hi>Sacred Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume</hi> had thus declar'd; Murmur not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35343:36"/>at theſe Orders, nor grudge ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Leavings; for, <hi>I am the Lord,</hi> you are but Tenants at Will: All you poſſeſs, is Mine: It is an Honour I do you, to give you the Title: You hold your Lands, your Lives, your All, of Me, by certain Services, and by Courteſie: <hi>I am the Lord;</hi> the Property Reſides in Me: There is nothing yours, at moſt, but by Will, or by Copy; ſo as you have no Right to Ingroſe the good things of this Life, or to hold them in durance. <hi>I am the Lord;</hi> from Me you receive all your Treaſure; therefore, fear not <hi>Poverty:</hi> I gave you this, and can give you more; take My Word, your <hi>Alms</hi> ſhall be doubled in Bleſſings, and reſtor'd into your Boſoms.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> were Commanded not only to be Charitable in the Field, but had a plain Statute for <hi>Alms-giving,</hi> at their own Houſes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. <hi>If there is a Poor Man among thy Brethren, within thy Gates, thou ſhalt not harden thy Heart, nor ſhut thy Hand from thy poor Brother; but thou ſhalt open thy Hand wide, and thy Heart
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35343:37"/>ſhall not be grieved, when thou Giveſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve in the Text, <hi>Three</hi> Motives to Compaſſion.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Man is <hi>Poor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. He is near in Blood, <hi>One among thy Brethren.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. He <hi>is within thy Gates.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Let his Poverty make you ſenſible of his Want: Let his Relation move you to Pity: Let his Neighbourhood inflame your Affection. And you may there take notice of Two directions in <hi>Giving:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Diſpence your <hi>Alms</hi> with a hand wide open; that is, Give Bountifully.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With a willing Heart, free from Grudging.</p>
            <p>Theſe latter Authorities are derived from the Law that was given at Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> Let us now here the Prophets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> maketh it a Characteriſtical Note of a good Man, to be Merciful; and holdeth giving <hi>Alms</hi> the beſt uſe of an Eſtate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 2. He nameth it the great work of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> to Defend
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35343:37"/>the Poor, Heal the Infirm, and Succour the Afflicted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> his Son, informs us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. 7. <hi>A Righteous Man conſidereth the cauſe of the Poor;</hi> adding in the 14. ver. of the ſame Chapter, <hi>The King that faithfully judgeth the Poor, ſhall have his Throne Eſtabliſhed:</hi> And this is the Wiſeſt of Monarchs.</p>
            <p>You may read in the Book of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> The way to Divine and <hi>Eternal Honour,</hi> is <hi>dealing thy Bread to the Hungry, lodging Exiles, covering the Naked;</hi> and, in a ſtrange Phraſe, to <hi>draw out thy Soul to the Empty:</hi> Then He continues, <hi>Thy Light ſhall ariſe from Obſcurity, thy priſtine Darkneſs ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Light, and reſemble the Sun in its Glory.</hi> This is the Evangelical Prophet.</p>
            <p>We read in the 22. Chap. of <hi>Ezekiel, GOD</hi> threatneth the <hi>Jews</hi> with many terrible Judgments, for <hi>Oppreſſing the Stranger,</hi> and <hi>Vexing the Fatherleſs and Widow.</hi> This is the Prieſt of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, transferr'd with <hi>Jehoiachim.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:35343:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> maketh <hi>Alms</hi> the trueſt ſign of ſincere Repentance; and will have <hi>Charity</hi> put into the definition of the Righteous. This is the Man of Viſions, to whom all Changes, which ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the <hi>Jews,</hi> from the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, to the general Reſurrection, was Revealed. Theſe preceded the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> and their Writings make the biggeſt part of the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi> Let us now conſult the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>To begin with the <hi>Baptiſt.</hi> Theſe <hi>Alms</hi> are the good Fruit He demands; Fruit fit for <hi>Penitents</hi> to produce. Our dear Maſter Preacheth the ſame Doctrine, St. <hi>Luke</hi> II. <hi>Give Alms of ſuch things as you have, and behold all things are clean unto you:</hi> As if <hi>C HRIST</hi> had told us, <hi>Alms</hi> are inſtead of all Levitical Purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations; and are accepted in Heaven ſooner than the curious Preſcription of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Love is a Flame that cleanſeth better than the Legal Rites; and a Fire that is conſiſtent with <hi>Holy Water;</hi> the ſmall Sacrifices of Chriſtian Love, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended in the <hi>New-Teſtament,</hi> have
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35343:38"/>Vertues Superior to the firſt Fruits, and thoſe greater ones of the <hi>Old-Teſtament:</hi> They have power to Sanctifie our Whole Eſtate, to make it Firm and Fertile, and to propagate it with our Iſſue. <hi>'Tis more Bleſſed to Give, than to Receive;</hi> that's a Maxim of the Bleſſed <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> which his Apoſtles and Diſciples did approve; and every true Chriſtian will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Peter</hi> mightily preſſeth us to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Love, and Hoſpitality, 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> cap. 1. ver. 22. <hi>Seeing you have purified your Souls, in Obeying the Truth, through the Spirit, and to unfeigned love of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſee that you love one another with pure Heart fervently.</hi> This is the Prince of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of nothing ſo much, as <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> 1 Ep. St. <hi>John,</hi> cap.4. <hi>Let us</hi> Love <hi>one another, for</hi> Love <hi>is of</hi> GOD, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> This is the Beloved Diſciple.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>James</hi> extols good Works much, and with ſome vehemence promotes <hi>Charity;</hi> deriding the <hi>Solifidian</hi> Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, that have nothing, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,]
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35343:39"/>beſides a ſtrong credulity; with which <hi>Julian</hi> upbraided ſome early Believers, that expected Salvation by Faith only. This <hi>James</hi> was the firſt Chriſtian Biſhop of the Holy City <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul,</hi> whoſe Writings too many wreſted to their own Deſtruction; which was one cauſe ſome other Apoſtles wrote ſo little, and ſome wrote nothing: He was careful and zealous to deal with the firſt Chriſtians of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> for a Collection, as St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>James,</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> had charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, when he firſt Travelled to make Proſelytes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. And this is the great Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will you have another added to theſe Four great Apoſtles. The Author of that Learned Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> writeth in this manner, <hi>To do Good, and to Communicate forget not; for with ſuch Sacrifices</hi> GOD <hi>is well pleaſed.</hi> If you will contend, that Epiſtle was Written by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> I ſhall be content to Humor you, ſeeing the Doctrine of good Works ſhall receive no diſparagement by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:35343:39"/>
            <p>Thus far the Duty hath been ratify'd by <hi>Precepts:</hi> But <hi>Examples</hi> are more forcible motives to Well-doing, and are as numerous in the Bible; pointing out to Chriſtians (as ſo many Mercuries) the direct way to Felicity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſitting at the door of his Tent, looketh for ſome weary Traveller, to whom he may give an Inſtance of his <hi>Charity;</hi> who, for his repeated Works of Mercy, deſerv'd the Reverend Title of the <hi>Father of the Faithful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lot,</hi> ſtanding at the Gate of his City, doth expect ſome diſtreſſed Stranger to make experiment of his Kindneſs, and Taſte his Hoſpitality; He gave the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Paſſenger a Meeting, leſt he ſhould be prevented in his Courteſies. This was an Oriental Prince and Prelate, Patron of the Five Cities, and Lord of <hi>Zoar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the cuſtom of <hi>Job,</hi> to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Fatherleſs in his Houſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite the Poor to his own Table. This Man, if you will have it ſo, was High-Prieſt of <hi>Hierapolis,</hi> and Prince in <hi>Arabia.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:35343:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> in ſuch Practiſes, was Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary; ſhewing himſelf in Love, as well as Empire, a Succeſſor to his Father <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> This Man, after <hi>God</hi>'s own Heart, thought himſelf not degraded by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Acts of Devotion and <hi>Charity.</hi> He knew how to reconcile Love and Honor; and reputed himſelf no leſs a King, for diſtributing, at certain Seaſons, a Loaf of Bread, a Flaggon of Wine, and a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Fleſh, to every ſingle Perſon of his decay'd Subjects.</p>
            <p>Obſerve how the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they were return'd from their Captivity, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated their Feſtivals with remarkable Contributions. Their Forms of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ended, they did enjoy themſelves in a generous participation of Delicacies; they drank freely, to Chearfulneſs, not to Exceſs, and diſpatcht away Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions to the Pooreſt Families, that they might be ſharers in the Joy, and the Feaſt, which they were not able to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh; and be made Partakers in the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude they paid to Heaven, by ſhewing themſelves pleas'd for National Bleſſings.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:35343:40"/>
            <p>We read <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. 33. of the Patriarchs Grove, which, the <hi>Rabbins</hi> inform us, was planted purpoſely for Charitable Entertainments; which they gather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Letters of the Name [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhel,</hi> a <hi>Grove</hi>] ſignifie by Cabaliſm, <hi>Meat, Drink,</hi> and <hi>Lodging;</hi> viz. <hi>Achilah, Sh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyan, Linah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To paſs from the <hi>Jews</hi> to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; How are the Churches of <hi>Achaia</hi> and <hi>Macedonia</hi> celebrated in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles, for their generous Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? The <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Alms</hi> of <hi>Cornelius</hi> aſcended to <hi>GOD,</hi> ſhewing their Maſter the way to Heaven: And tho' both are very laudable, yet the Fathers aſcribe to <hi>Alms</hi> the preheminence.</p>
            <p>So to Live, and practice Religion, is to accompliſh the Laws, and comply with the Will of <hi>Solomon:</hi> 'Tis to do more than that comes to; for <hi>Solomon</hi> was but a Type of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> But to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Love, is to follow the ſteps of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, and to obey the Dictates of the Supream Maſter; who, having no Purſe-bearer for Himſelf, had always
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:35343:41"/>a Treaſurer for the Diſtreſſed; and daily wrought Miracles, to ſatisfie their Wants in the Wilderneſs; chooſing rather to Faſt <hi>Forty Days,</hi> than to multiply Loaves for appeaſing his own Hunger; He ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Houſe to hide his Head in, laid his Commands upon the Heavens, that his Followers might be freed from the Injuries of the ill Weather. While he was contentedly depriv'd of ordinary conveniencies, He was not contented his Diſciples ſhould ſuffer; but, for their ſakes, made uſe of his Divinity, that He might ſhew Himſelf Hoſpitable in the Deſart.</p>
            <p>'Tis not for <hi>Men</hi> alone to pretend to, or claim the Glory that attends Chriſtian Love; for <hi>Women</hi> ſeem naturally more Compaſſionate. Sacred and Prophane Story will furniſh us with Infinite Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of their <hi>Charity:</hi> The <hi>Zereptan</hi> Widdow, to relieve the Prophet <hi>Eliah,</hi> hazzards the Pining of her ſelf, and her Son, and puts to the adventure, all the ſad accidents of a miſerable Famine. Another caſt Two Mites into the <hi>Corban,</hi> (or Sacred Treaſury) from which the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35343:41"/>Poor of all ſorts were Relieved. It was her Whole Pittance; and to approve her ſelf Charitable, ſhe runs the Risk of the moſt diſconſolate effects of Poverty. <hi>Charity</hi> (the Name is Feminine, and) hath always been Pictur'd in the Shape, and with the Features of a Beautiful Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: The Chriſtian Church takes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the rehearſal of the Names of her loving, and her officious Daughters: She hath many ſuch as <hi>Dorcas,</hi> that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy, and pleaſe themſelves in Lodging Strangers; in working admirable Pieces for Temples and Altars; and deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Studies and Portions for the publick Uſes of True Religion. They exerciſe their Chriſtian Vertues, by giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Alms</hi> daily, Waſhing the Saints Feet, Viſiting the Sick, and Comforting all thoſe that are in any manner of Affliction.</p>
            <p>Credible Hiſtorians acquaint us with the Hoſpitality of the Ancient City <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinore,</hi> in <hi>Italy;</hi> how the Burgeſſes vyed Bounty, &amp; ſtrived to exceed one another, in putting Obligations upon Strangers. So great was their emulation to do good,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35343:42"/>that, in ſine, they determin'd to Erect a Collume in their Market, to which Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Rings in Plates were faſtened; upon thoſe Plates, the Names of all the Noted Families in Town were Engraven'd; all Strangers were carried thither, and made choice of one of thoſe Names for their Reception: The Houſe, to which the Stranger by choice deſir'd to reſort, was forthwith inform'd, by one of the daily Waiters; the Maſter of the Family there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon came rejoycing, and conducted his Gueſts, that was ſometimes miſerable Poor, to his Houſe, with ſigns of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph: And, why not? ſeeing <hi>Charity</hi> goes attended with Reward and Victory.</p>
            <p>'Tis not always, that we ought to do well with ſo much Solemnity: For many times, Works of Mercy are beſt perform'd with privacy. <hi>Sound not a Trumpet when thou giveſt Alms,</hi> ſays our dear Maſter, St. <hi>Matthew</hi> 6. No, not a Trumpet, ſays <hi>Chryſologus;</hi> becauſe ſuch Kindneſs, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with a Noiſe, cometh not ſo much like a Friend, as like an Enemy: It ſeems to Inſult over the Wants of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35343:42"/>Receiver, and to aſſault his Modeſty. This is not to Relieve ſo much, as to Triumph over thy poor Brother. It is worſe: It is an upbraiding of <hi>GOD,</hi> as if He was beholding to your Favour, and could not enable that poor Heart to Subſiſt without your <hi>Charity.</hi> If that be the <hi>Engliſh</hi> way of giving <hi>Alms,</hi> ſuch Donors muſt pay themſelves with the popular Name of <hi>Patriots,</hi> or Benefactors to the Publick. They muſt forbear their Pretenſions to future Recompence; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Great Maſter declares, they have their <hi>Reward.</hi> The prevailing Prayers of the Poor, and the never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>failing Promiſe of <hi>GOD,</hi> ſhall prove but of ſmall advantage to their miſtaken Souls, that had no reſpect to either of them, in their <hi>Alms-giving,</hi> but only to the Applauſe of the People.</p>
            <p>Let it ſuffice, that <hi>GOD</hi> diſcerns thy Bounty; make Him only thy Witneſs, that is to be thy Judge; and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>GOD</hi> ſhall make Requital, that knows how much confidence you repoſe in his Juſtice. You may remain aſſur'd,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35343:43"/>He that would not have the Left-hand know what the Right-hand giveth, will not allow you to tell them that will tell every Body, how much you beſtow. Give <hi>Alms</hi> there, where there is no Man to diſcover it, and <hi>Thy Father, which ſeeth in Secret, will Reward you openly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we have Traverſt the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> Let us proceed to the <hi>Promiſe; Thou ſhalt find thy Bread, after many Days,</hi> which thou doſt caſt upon the <hi>Waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing Riches are valuable Bleſſings, ſuch as afford us in this Life no deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Comforts; it concerns us to know, for whoſe ſake, &amp; upon what account, we caſt them away; for it is ſomewhat to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive our ſelves, and our Poſterity, of their Service: Hear me, therefore, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Charitable Practices of the Church, to be ſounded upon the higheſt Reaſon. You will be loath to part with your Treaſure, but upon the beſt Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; you ſhall have the beſt Word of a <hi>King,</hi> and a <hi>Prieſt;</hi> and They are both
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35343:43"/>inviolable. <hi>Solomon</hi> ingages his Honour, that <hi>you ſhall find it;</hi> which is as much as to ſecure you, you ſhall be no Loſers. What you ſcatter upon the Waves, doth not Periſh; but the Stream will return to reſtore your Kindneſs.</p>
            <p>Have you never ſeen a Ship, of good Burthen, Laden with the Richeſt Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, Arrive in a ſafe Haven? She carries out of the Owners ſight; She makes a Voyage of many days; yet, at length, ſhe returns her Treaſure upon the Exchange, and brings the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turer an advantageous <hi>Cargo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Ship may be wrackt, and there the Lading may Periſh: But <hi>Here</hi> you run no ſuch hazzard: For, ſuppoſing the <hi>Poor</hi> ſhould Miſcarry, your <hi>Alms</hi> will be ſafely conveyed to the Port; for the Bearer is no ſooner out of your Door, or the Gift out of your Hand, but <hi>GOD</hi> takes it into his Protection and Cuſtody: Holy Angels are the Convoy, and <hi>CHRIST</hi> looking upon the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, now to be Conſecrated, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to ballance all Loſſes. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35343:44"/>of Gains, to place to the Donor's Account, and of a way to double your Intereſt: The Lord chargeth himſelf with the Gift, where-ever it is; and therefore doth not allow you to demand or expect Repayment, by Word or Deed, from a Third Perſon.</p>
            <p>Let it be the part of <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners,</hi> to Feaſt their thriving Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; while He that deſigns to perform Acts of <hi>Charity,</hi> muſt, by his Invitations, make the <hi>Sick,</hi> the <hi>Blind,</hi> and the <hi>Lame,</hi> his Gueſts, and thoſe poor People that want a Dinner: So ſhall he be Bleſſed; ſo ſhall he make himſelf a growing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt: If he dare take the Word of the World's <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> he ſhall not fail to be Rewarded at the Reſurrection of the Juſt, St. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. which ſome offer to aſſert, ſhall precede the general Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. The Reward is certain, <hi>Thou ſhalt find it;</hi> the Terms are poſitive. Our good Deeds cannot paſs unregarded: Not a Cup of cold Water; not a Morſel of Bread, ſhall eſcape <hi>GOD</hi>'s Notice, or fall ſhort of His remuneration.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:35343:44"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt find it; Thou</hi> thy ſelf. 'Tis a ſtrange Kindneſs, that all Perſons have for their own Fleſh and Blood: Men are now a-days, more than ever, Lovers of themſelves; and they will adventure that upon their own Heads, which they dare not truſt upon the Heads of their Children and Relations. What Man is he, that poſſeſſeth an Eſtate or Honors, which he deſireth not to continue for ever? Behold a way to preſerve your Dignities, and hold your Mannors to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity! Convert them into <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Bread, and <hi>Caſt them upon the Waters;</hi> it will prove pregnant of Bleſſings, and, reſembling good Seed, it will continue to grow and ripen, and to yield an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Harveſt: <hi>You ſhall find it, after many days,</hi> in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Man as Solicitous as can be, to Get and Save; 'tis not in his Power to ſecure his Eſtate upon Earth, ſo much as to the Fourth Generation. Notwithſtanding his Gains, he has no certainty, but that Poverty ſhall ſeize his Sons or Nephews: But if you covet, to ſecure your Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35343:45"/>to the Third and Fourth Generation, take the Meaſures here preſcrib'd by <hi>Solomon.</hi> You ſhall not only leave an Aſſurance to the Third Heir, but you ſhall alſo retain what you give away: And, changing the Property by thoſe <hi>Alms</hi> you beſtow, you ſhall both make it theirs, and your own for ever. 'Tis only ſo much of your Eſtate, that you can poſſibly loſe, as you are not free to impart: For all that you give in the way of <hi>Charity,</hi> you ſhall ſurely find; and reckon ſo much goeth towards the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Spiritual Body the more Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; and to purchaſe for you one of thoſe many Manſions, in the Houſe of our Heavenly Father; where every to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Chriſtian Love ſhall appear an Ornament to the Donor, to render him bright as a Star, and ſerve his Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, inſtead of Painting and Coroniſh. Why, good <hi>Sir,</hi> ſhould you then demand or expect a Requital at the Hand of him that Receiveth the Boon? As if you knew not the Man to be <hi>GOD</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver; or, as if you were altogether
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35343:45"/>unacquainted with the Diſpoſition of that Juſt and Bountiful Maſter he ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth. Would you have many Thanks return'd? Or, would you be highly Courted? Or, baſely Flatter'd out of your Benevolence? Thanks and Praiſes are but indifferent Bribes; they pay no Debts, but only ſerve to corrupt Servile Spirits: Make your ſelf greater than that, and manifeſt more Honour than that comes to; for to disburſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Summs for thoſe baſe ends, is no part of <hi>Charity,</hi> but an ill Exchange.</p>
            <p>Where real Effects are Bartered for Oyly Words, and Slaviſh Geſtures; <hi>[Gratis non datur quod gratiis venditur,]</hi> ſo doing, you ſell your Kindneſs, and make but a bad Market; becauſe, at the ſame time, you loſe Poſſeſſion of that you had, and loſe ſight of your Pay-Maſter. If that be your way to diſtribute <hi>Bread,</hi> for the ſake of reſpective Honours and Addreſs, you muſt compound with them for the whole Debt; and accepting leſs than half Pay, for the Whole, take your leave of additional Bleſſings, and future
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35343:46"/>Glory; chuſing to take the Word of a a <hi>Beggar,</hi> rather than the Word of <hi>GOD;</hi> you loſe, at an Inſtant, both your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration and Requital.</p>
            <p>When your meaning is to find your <hi>Bread,</hi> give it upon <hi>GOD</hi>'s Account, that <hi>GOD</hi> may become your Debtor; ſo ſhall the <hi>Bread</hi> thou doſt diſpenſe, nouriſh thy own Soul unto Life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            <p>Thou caſteſt <hi>Bread</hi> upon the <hi>Waters,</hi> which vary themſelves in many Figures, and often change their condition; yet, through the Divine Power, and Truth, 'tis reſerv'd for your Uſe, and the <hi>Bread</hi> is found again; intimating, how the Subſtance of all things is perſerv'd en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and lives Eternally.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bread</hi> which you lately did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, you have given over for loſt: 'Tis not ſo, your Fear impoſeth upon your Reaſon; the ſame ſhall be return'd in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Nature, and in a larger meaſure. How, are you qualified to Receive, but are not contented to Give? Is it your deſign to put limits to Providence, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35343:46"/>confine this World to reſt in your Coffers, that was created in Motion?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Gift</hi> is put here, by an happy Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, for that Fruit and Recompenſe, which, after many days, follows the Act of Giving, it is ſo contriv'd, to render the Giver as certain of the One, as ever he was ſure of the Other: As there is upon Earth, a Communion of Saints, maintain'd by certain Spiritual Acts of <hi>Devotion,</hi> mixt with <hi>Charity;</hi> ſo there is an everlaſting Retaliation between <hi>Alms,</hi> and its Recompenſe.</p>
            <p>There is a Time ſet down (tho' not many circumſtances of it,) when the Charitable Perſon ſhall be Rewarded, <hi>after many Days,</hi> ſays the Royal Preacher; ſo I thought, ſays the Miſer, my patience will be tyred with waiting, for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of my Money; it will be long, you ſay, (and I know not how long) e're I ſhall be the better for that I give away. Doth my Father lye the eaſier in his Grave, for the Legacy he left to the Poor of the Pariſh? His condition might have been more eaſie [Chuff]
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35343:47"/>had he beſtow'd upon his Son better <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation;</hi> all his Cares and Prayers are loſt upon you, his Succeſſor; that ſhew your ſelf ungrateful to Heaven, and to your Parents.</p>
            <p>I leave you to Time and Torment, to correct your Miſtake; but know, theſe words (<hi>After many Days</hi>) carry their own weight; a Senſe ſo pleaſing, and include an Argument ſo ſtrong, that when you, and your Ingratitude, are Buried together, it ſhall ſerve to oblige Generations to come to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this Duty. 'Tis <hi>After many Days,</hi> the Charitable Man is ſaid to find his <hi>Bread;</hi> to ſignifie, he ſhall live many Days; his Life ſhall not be ſhortned, neither ſhall his Death be ſudden: But his Days ſhall be prolong'd in this World, meerly that he may do good in his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Wicked and Blood-Thirſty Man ſhall not live out half his Days;</hi> for <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> you may read <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable,</hi> becauſe the greater part of Wickedneſs proceeds from a defect of <hi>Charity.</hi> But there
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35343:47"/>ſhall be Days added to the Bountiful Man's Years, as to <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s; until his Years, with his Vertues, encreaſe beyond the number of his Hairs, and procure for him everlaſting Benedictions, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt find it after many Days:</hi> 'Tis as if the <hi>Wiſe-Man</hi> had ſaid, Thou ſhalt live many Days, to do good with thy Riches; and, when thou haſt finiſht thy Courſe, of multiplying good Offices to thy Brethren; then, <hi>After many Days,</hi> thou ſhalt find an Heavenly Treaſure, to the Accompliſhment of thy Felicity. Think not the time long, becauſe the Pay is certain; think it not tedious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe at that time, Bleſſings are grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for thy Comfort, and multiplying for thy Uſe and Advantage. Why ſhould you think the Time long, when all Time is inconſiderable, leſs than a Minute, compar'd with that Eternity, which ſhall afford you an Abyſs of Joys, and Treaſures, that can never Periſh?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt find it after many Days:</hi> There is a Time ſet a part, in the ſecret
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35343:48"/>Will of <hi>GOD,</hi> wherein the Lord hath decreed to make you a plenary Requital. Not of ſome Earthly thing, which is Tranſitory; but full Pay, and of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Spiritual, Glorious, and Permament. It may be, what you give away to Day, you would have again to Morrow; the Seed you Sow, doth not grow with that Expedition; you muſt allow it Time to dye, and to revive again; and to grow, before it can ripen to Harveſt: But you dare truſt <hi>Earth</hi> further than <hi>Heaven.</hi> If you will have your Reward before its due time, you muſt have it imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as immature Fruit gather'd out of Seaſon.</p>
            <p>But, my Advice is, and it is <hi>Solomon</hi>'s, To give it leave to come to Perfection; ſo ſhall you be ſure to find it, <hi>After ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Days,</hi> ſuch as you deſire to have it, in all points abſolute.</p>
            <p>'Tis the Will of <hi>GOD,</hi> that as He for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears to Puniſh us many Days, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Days waits for our Amendments; ſo we ſhould add <hi>Patience</hi> to <hi>Charity,</hi> that, at once, the Two Vertues may be Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:35343:48"/>
            <p>However, for our greater Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there are preſent Renumerations appointed for thoſe that are Charitable; they ſhall have their Wiſhes very much gratify'd in this World, and in the World to come, their Hopes ſhall expire in a happy Fruition. Here, in this Life, you ſhall receive the Wages of Love, in a good meaſure; but, in the next, you ſhall enjoy what you expect in a ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory manner; or, as the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe reads it, <hi>Plenarily.</hi> For indeed, theſe words, <hi>After many Days,</hi> are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally referr'd to the Reſurrection, and future Glory. Can you pretend to Chriſtian <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> and at the ſame time, Deſpair and Murmur? Will you preſcribe your <hi>GOD</hi> the Time, any more than the Method of Payment? Hear the Voice of our Saviour! <hi>Lo, I come.</hi> Yet you ſay, Where is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his Coming? If there be many Days before <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Advent, there is the greater Preparation making for your Reception; and when He comes, you will be fully ſatisfied for attending the Lord's Leiſure.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:35343:49"/>
            <p>Shorten not your Hand of Relief, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>GOD</hi> payeth Intereſt, for the whole Time of your Forbearance: You ſpoyl your Recompence, by coveting to have it ſuddenly. Comfort your ſelf in recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the good Offices you have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd; and in a good Conſcience in <hi>GOD</hi>'s Promiſe, and in Comforts of this Life, that are ordinarily conferr'd and enjoy'd by the Charitable Perſon, as ſure Earneſt of a future Reward. Have a little Patience, the Days may be <hi>many;</hi> yet, at moſt, they are but <hi>Days,</hi> that will ſoon expire. Perſiſt in your Godly purpoſes; 'Tis not long, e're Mercies will plentifully return into your Boſom.</p>
            <p>The Time of waiting is not expreſt by <hi>Tears, or Months,</hi> nor by ſo much as <hi>Weeks;</hi> but only by <hi>Days,</hi> that quickly come to their Period. <hi>Days</hi> are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, becauſe a <hi>Day</hi> receives denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from, and has reference to the <hi>Sun</hi>'s Motion; importing, how <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Son of Righteouſneſs, hath in this <hi>Day</hi> many great Works to perform in the Hearts of the Faithful; many Divine
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35343:49"/>Graces to quicken; many Methods of Holineſs, and Meaſures of Redemption to finiſh; we muſt not antedate our own or others Happineſs. When the Work of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is perfect in us, we ſhall ſurely find the Reward of our <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come then with a chearful Heart, and a Liberal Hand; give the World an Inſtance of that Love and Bounty, which appears in imparting much to many; and ſhows it ſelf with advantage in the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the Gift, and the multitude of Receivers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that Soweth Bountifully,</hi> (or as the <hi>Greek</hi> readeth, in <hi>Bleſſings</hi>) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>ſhall Reap in Benedictions and plentifully.</hi> The Apoſtle there proveth, That the ſame Aſſurance the Seed-Man has of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, according to the proportion of his Sowing, that <hi>GOD</hi> will multiply his Favours upon the <hi>Alms-giver,</hi> with equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent augmentations of Glory.</p>
            <p>It was <hi>David</hi>'s way of Praying, and ought to be ours, <hi>Have Mercy upon us, O Lord, according to the multitude of thy Mercies:</hi> Which is ſo far Doctrinal, that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35343:50"/>we muſt afford a multitude of Mercies to our poor Brethren; and then we may approach the Throne of Grace with boldneſs, having Aſſurance that our Petitions will be Anſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſhall find it, after many Days,</hi> ſays the Royal Preacher; and, tho' a Miſer may refuſe it, yet a good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ought to look upon <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Word, as better Security than Bond and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. You are to have Regard to the poor Man's Wants, and at the ſame time, to your own Ability; and confiding in Providence, are to Give rather more than your Eſtate can afford; for ſuch is the Advice of the diſcreet Noble-man to his Son; <hi>Tobit,</hi> Chap. 4. <hi>Of abundance, Give accerdingly. Of a Little, be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of giving Alms of that Little; for thereby th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u boardeſt up to thy ſelf Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt the day of Neceſſity.</hi> Did I not tell you this before? His Opinion agrees with mine; You are to live upon the thing only which you gave away. It follows in the 10. Verſe of that 4. Chap. <hi>Alms deliver from Death;</hi> meaning
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35343:50"/>Death Eternal: Where you find, in what manner you ſhall be repaid your Acts of <hi>Charity,</hi> with Life everlaſting.</p>
            <p>But ſtill you Haeſitate, and look as if you would Reply, I am very loath to part with a preſent Eſtate, without a preſent valuable Conſideration: That is your Miſtake; you part with no preſent Eſtate, and you receive that, at preſent, which ought to be your ſatisfaction. What would you be Recompenſed for? you have ſo much only, as you can uſe; the reſidue you fancy to be yours; but there is no more yours, than you can enjoy; of a Thouſand Mannors, and Ten Thouſand Droves of Cattle, theſe may pleaſe your Eye, and your Conceit, and with the thoughts of Poſſeſſing, you may ſatisfie your hungry Humours; but, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, another ſhall enjoy as much as you. Your Parks, Woods, Warrens, and your Game, with all the Delights and Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantries of your Family; out of all theſe, you can take no more than Meat, Drink, and Cloathing; for which, a ſmall Eſtate would ſuffice. But, here, you are Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35343:51"/>to many, having wherewithal to do good; that is, many good things truſted to your diſpoſal; and, here, you have a ready way pointed out, to make a Temporal Income to become Spiritual and Eternal: for, only by giving <hi>Alms,</hi> you ſhall lay up for your ſelf Treaſure in Heaven, of which you can never be depriv'd; and you ſhall forthwith receive ſome Temporal ſatisfaction, for your Acts of <hi>Charity.</hi> For the Merciful Man never fails of particular Bleſſings in this Life, by Health, Strength, Wit, Peace, Preſervation from Dangers, by ſure Friends, by a good Wife, by hopeful Children, by ſecret Contentment in the Mind, and Joy that is unſpeakable; by a clear Reputation, and quiet Conſcience: By ſome or more of theſe Enjoyments, the Charitable Perſon ſhall immediately find his <hi>Bread,</hi> that he hath ſcatter'd upon the <hi>Waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Placing, therefore, One Eye upon your preſent Condition, fix the Other on the poor Man's Neceſſities; and let the fight of his Miſeries, be the Rule of your
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35343:51"/>Mercies; for, in <hi>Alms-giving,</hi> much is but a little, where more is wanting; and a little is much, where that little ſufficeth.</p>
            <p>Let the greedy Chuff plead a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of thine and mine: Let him do what he can to ſecure Property: Let him Intail his Lands, and enterprize all he may, to confirm his Title, or inlarge his Poſſeſſions: Let him call <hi>Good Works</hi> a kind of Community, and oppoſe <hi>Alms</hi> as much as levelling: Let him ſay, All that I hold, is mine; and what wrong can I commit, by keeping my own to my ſelf? For my part, <hi>Sir,</hi> I love Peace and Plenty; your Speech-making ought to be directed to them, that affect Lawleſs Lives, or Civil-Wars, ſeeking to deprive others of their Rights, and their Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. I ſhould like <hi>Religion</hi> better, if the Teachers were not as ſo many Leaches, Give, give, continually; I love to hear them Preach up <hi>Chriſt</hi> Crucify'd, and forbear their old <hi>Popiſh</hi> Stories of <hi>Alms</hi> and <hi>Good-Works:</hi> You know, there was no Beggar in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and, were I
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:35343:52"/>Task-Maſter General, there ſhould be none leſt in <hi>England.</hi> But, I think, of all poor People, the poor Gentleman is the moſt importunate; his Hands is always full of <hi>Briefs,</hi> and <hi>Letters</hi> of Requeſt; and I ſeldom ſee one of that Tribe, but I am feeling in my Pocket.</p>
            <p>When you have ſpoken your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>Nabal,</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſtian Love,</hi> and <hi>Charitable Contributions,</hi> it is but one way of wounding your ſelf with your own Weapon; ſeeing the way to make that you poſſeſs your own, is by your power of diſpoſal: Which, if it be never put into Act, how can you be aſſured you have ſuch a Power. By giving it a-way, we come to know it is yours; and, as without <hi>Property,</hi> there can be no <hi>Charity;</hi> ſo <hi>Charity,</hi> in its ſeveral Acts, doth beſt confirm <hi>Property:</hi> From the Laws of <hi>Thine</hi> and <hi>Mine,</hi> you bring an ill Inference, whereas, by Giving, thoſe Laws are beſt put in Execution: You muſt give, not only for the Preſervation of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> but alſo for the maintenance of your Title. Unleſs the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35343:52"/>
               <hi>Bread</hi> be yours, how can you diſpoſe of it? There is neither <hi>Giving,</hi> nor Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation by <hi>Gift,</hi> where all is in common. If you peruſe the principal Cauſes, of the firſt diſtinction between <hi>Mine</hi> and <hi>Thine,</hi> long ago confirm'd by Cuſtom, by the Poſitive Laws of <hi>GOD,</hi> and of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; you will find theſe, among others:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Encouragement to Labour,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Idleneſs; for, where the moſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious, and the moſt Negl gent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, were to be ſharers alike of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fund, too many would lye basking in the Sun, while others were Sweating at their Imployment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>For Preſervation of Peace;</hi> they being moſt remote from War, that have moſt to loſe; who cannot ſoon be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to Fight, ſo long as they can qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly enjoy their Effects, and Fruits of their Labour and Induſtry.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>To diſtinguiſh Families;</hi> becauſe it appears the Will of Heaven, that ſome Houſes ſhould be remarkable for <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> ſome for <hi>Vertues;</hi> and that ſome ſhould be ſtiled, from their Inheriting of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35343:53"/>Riches, <hi>Generous</hi> and <hi>Noble;</hi> while others ſhould be noted, for a <hi>Dull,</hi> and <hi>Idle Generation,</hi> born under Command, to remain Slaves and Peaſants.</p>
            <p>With this diſtinction, of <hi>Thine</hi> and <hi>Mine,</hi> began a Subordination of Men in Civil Societies, for the ſake of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. But, of all theſe cauſes of difference of Eſtates, none is greater than this, That there might be ſome Endowed with Riches, to impart; and that there might be ſome poor People, to make tryal of the Rich Man's Faith in <hi>GOD</hi>'s Promiſes, and deſign'd for his own Good, to make Experiment upon his <hi>Charity:</hi> That, by contributing much in <hi>this Life,</hi> he might obtain, in the <hi>next,</hi> a more Illuſtrious and laſting Inheritance. Art thou a Propriator? yet you muſt own a Lord in chief of all your Subſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Earth is the Lord's, and the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof;</hi> all Lands are held of him in <hi>Capire:</hi> So, to alleadge Property, when <hi>GOD</hi> Commands you to dirburſe ſomething upon his Account, is to ſay
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35343:53"/>ſomewhat that is anſwer'd by the Laws of Supream Right, and ſuſpended by the degrees of <hi>Charity.</hi> It is enough, that you have the Honour, and the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Diſtribution, and to reſerve e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for your own Uſes: Take what ſufficeth for your Family, defraud not your Succeſſors; and behold thoſe poor People yonder, are ſent to be Sharers of all that is to be ſpar'd from You, and your Poſterity: If <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to you, the <hi>ſame</hi> preſently becomes one of their Neceſſaries: And what you reſerve, cannot be ſo much your own, becauſe it is over-plus to your Uſe every way, unleſs you put it to Intereſt, to that Company of <hi>Beads-Men:</hi> For, at the Inſtant you diſpoſe it to them, the ſame is entered in the Day-Book of Heaven; and out of that Treaſure, you ſhall be Repaid: And you ſhall find it, <hi>After many Days,</hi> infinitely multiply'd.</p>
            <p>Obſerve, how Nature communicates; The <hi>Sun,</hi> out of his abundance of Light, gives a Largeſs of it to the <hi>Moon; Lucinoe</hi> gives Alms of the Light ſhe receives to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35343:54"/>the Earth, that is founded in Darkneſs: This <hi>Earth,</hi> having no Light to ſpare, freely imparts ſuch uſeful Matters, as ſhe carries, though of another Growth and Temper, to her ingrateful Inhabitants: The <hi>Clouds,</hi> newly repleniſht with Rain, empty their Stores upon the parched Mountains; they diſcharging themſelves into the Rivers that over-flow, pay Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the wide Ocean. <hi>Nilus</hi> and <hi>Euphrates</hi> are proud, in ſwelling over their Banks, to make the adjoyning Meadows Fertile. The glutted <hi>Bear</hi> and <hi>Tyger,</hi> have ſometimes quitted their Prey, to others half pin'd, and to Beaſts leſs Ravenous; while the more Civiller Creatures of every Species, have been famous in Story, for many tokens of Affection; ſhewing how all things, from the higheſt to the loweſt, correſpond for a mutual Relief: Here and there is an accurſed <hi>Shimei,</hi> or a churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> excepted; that ſays, Who is <hi>David?</hi> Talk not to me of the <hi>King,</hi> or the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet;</hi> I know not that Man in the World, for whoſe ſake I would little my Eſtate:
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35343:54"/>Shall I take my <hi>Bread,</hi> and give it to Strangers? It is enough, <hi>Churle,</hi> that you know the Petitioners to be Men; and, that you may know, every Man is of more value, than a Mint of Gold and Silver: Would you loſe a Man, for a Morſel of <hi>Bread?</hi> Shall I take my <hi>Bread,</hi> and give it away, doſt thou ſay? 'Tis thy <hi>Bread,</hi> indeed, by the Favour of a better Maſter than thou art; but ſo, that it is not always, and every way thine. There is a certain Clauſe in the Conveyance, that ſpeaks it thy <hi>Bread</hi> to <hi>Give,</hi> not thine to <hi>with-hold:</hi> 'Tis yours to <hi>diſpoſe of,</hi> not to <hi>detain;</hi> the diſpoſal of which, looks toward the <hi>Communion of Saints</hi> that is on Earth, with thoſe in Heaven.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>Bread</hi> of participation in every Houſe, as the <hi>Euchariſtical Bread</hi> is eminently ſuch in Churches: And, for maintaining a Correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Divine and Humane Love, and their Effects, we are taught to make daily Petitions: 'Tis you, <hi>Miſer,</hi> that makes bold to change our Lord's Form of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35343:55"/>Prayer; calling that <hi>Your Bread,</hi> in your ſelfiſh Language, which is call'd <hi>Our Bread,</hi> in the Language of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; And that is, and ought to be the <hi>Idiom</hi> of all good Chriſtians. Which word [<hi>Our</hi>] doth import a Chriſtian Communication.</p>
            <p>Shall I take my <hi>Bread,</hi> and <hi>Caſt it upon the Waters?</hi> How dare you put ſuch a Queſtion? <hi>Impudent Man,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> What is thine but thy Sins? Did you command the <hi>Earth</hi> to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh it? the <hi>Clouds</hi> to Water it? the <hi>Sun</hi> to Ripen it? What was yours when you came into this World, Mourning and Naked? What Silver and Gold did'ſt thou bring in thy hands? What Furniture for a Houſe? What Garments for a Covering? Your Pride, in ſuch Queſtions, doth wrong to your Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for, all you Poſſeſs, you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd. The Richeſt Heir muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge himſelf beholding to the Rule of <hi>Charity.</hi> Here you found all at your Entrance, and Here you ſhall leave all at your Departure; you ſhall
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35343:55"/>not carry with you ſo much, as is ſpent upon your <hi>Obſequies.</hi> All theſe things you ſo much covet and hoard, without asking your leave, will ſtay behind; unleſs you take this only ſure way to make them yours, and carry them with you, by the proceeding Methods of <hi>Charity:</hi> That is a way, that will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly convey your Lands and Goods to your future Uſe; which will at once, by Sanctifying them, dedicate them E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally to your Service.</p>
            <p>To ſecure thoſe unjuſt Gettings of your <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> and make ſuch a firm Settlement of your Eſtate, as you deſire to be made at the ſame time on your Poſterity; you muſt take <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Counſel; for ſo will it wear well, and endure many <hi>Generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hear me farther: Is not he, that puts this Queſtion, like the ſame Man, that, in a few late Years got an Eſtate by Fraud and Oppreſſion? And dare you ſay, Shall I <hi>Caſt</hi> my <hi>Bread upon the Waters,</hi> when all the Goods you poſſeſs, may be ſo many private Wrongs, or publick
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35343:56"/>Grievances? Call them no more <hi>Thine,</hi> for which you rob'd Innocents, ſtript Honeſt Men Naked, and forc'd others to Beggary. You ſay, Muſt a Man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh Himſelf, to relieve Strangers? You have a Family to maintain, Rents to pay, Farms to ſtock, and Houſes to furniſh; ſo that you ſet an Honeſt Care, in oppoſition to <hi>Divine Charity,</hi> and give the Servant the upper-hand of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs: Whereas this Coeleſtial Vertue, demands only what may be ſpared, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] ſuch as are rather Ornaments, and Complements of your condition, than neceſſaries of Nature; tho' theſe alſo be required, to ſave the Life of a publick Perſon of your deareſt Friends, and near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Relations.</p>
            <p>But your State and Place require all your have, and more: Believe me, No! both Commands you to be Charitable: Your Honour is engaged by your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerment, to do good according to your Title; whatever is abſolutely neceſſary to your Perſon, is not to be ſequeſtred by <hi>Charity,</hi> which calls for only ſo much
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35343:56"/>as may be ſpar'd from your Perſon, and your Dignity; for all that appertains to diſtreſſed Objects, is, as to you, Superfluous. Fear not, <hi>Solomon</hi> requires none of your Neceſſaries, but your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings: He deſires no prejudice to your Body, but to your Vices; and, ſeeking your Health, offers you means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Diſeaſes. Cannot you ſpare one Diſh of Meat, one Loaf of Bread, one Coat, of many, one Shilling oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely, to keep Life in a poor Body.</p>
            <p>Here me, <hi>Sir;</hi> Feed more at your Gates, and fewer in your Mews, Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, and Stables; Conſider, how you disburſe in needleſs Accoutrements, in Forreign Toys, in altering and furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Houſes. This Turret, that Cupolo might be ſpared; theſe Marble Columns, yonder Trraſs-Walks; theſe Thorough-Lights, them Tapiſtry Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; that Garniſhing, thoſe Orient Jewels, be mighty chargable: I could have ſpared much of this coſtly Pearl; and, with ſome of that, I would have caſed ſome poor Tenants: I would have
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35343:57"/>Imploy'd ſome poor Labourers, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd ſome poor Captives; I would have Lodged and Victualled ſome poor Travellers; I would have ſet ſome poor Priſoners for Debt at Liberty; I would have placed ſome poor Orphans Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices; and have given Portions for the Marriage of ſome poor Maidens: Some College, or School of good Literature, ſhould have been Endowed; ſome Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Founded, &amp;c. So ſhould you make a competent Proviſion for your ſelves, Here, and Hereafter acquire Manſions of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: So ſhould you Live in favour of <hi>God</hi> and Man, and obtain that due Reſpect from your Neighbours, which your Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and Vanity now makes Counterfeit, by thus begining to be Frugal at the right end; for <hi>Charity</hi> hath converted many Prodigals from Extravagant Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and, by making them Maſters of themſelves, hath made them Lord of great Eſtates; of which <hi>Chriſtian Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> thoſe only may complain, that have ſmall Experience.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
